(inquisitive music)
(upbeat music)
(John sighs and claps)
- The Middle East, the part
of Asia that Europeans see
as the middle of what
they see as the east.
Sort of arbitrary. Whatever,
we call it the Middle East.
This part of the world
is literally where civilization started,
right here, in modern-day Iraq.
And over the years,
the borders here have
been redrawn many times
as empires have ebbed and
flowed through this region.
By the way, I didn't make this time lapse.
A very talented YouTuber did,
and he deserves a medal for it.
(fanfare music)
Or perhaps just a new patron. Thanks, man.
Anyway, the most recent
carving up of this region
happened by European powers,
the French, the British, the Russians.
I mean, are we surprised? No.
Like, of course. Of
course it was the British.
Of course it was the French.
Of course it was Europeans. Of course.
The lines they drew didn't
really take into account language
or ethnicity or regional identity.
They just sort of sliced it
all up amongst themselves
and said, "These are
our new regions of power
in the Middle East."
Eventually, those European powers left,
but the lines they drew stuck
around and became the skeleton
for what the borders look like today.
And this is where our story starts,
in the 1930s, here in
the modern Middle East.
At this point, across the ocean,
there was this growing superpower
that had spent the last
century moving west,
taking over this whole
continent and beyond,
deep into the Pacific Ocean.
We've talked about that a bit.
But things were changing.
The world had just
fought a brutal world war
that was fought with new weapons
that were powered by this
new important substance, oil.
Germany lost that war,
in part because they didn't
have access to enough oil
to keep up with this new style of warfare
that relied a lot more on machines.
The young superpower realized
that access to this stuff
would determine who would be
powerful and who would not.
So they stopped looking west
for a moment and turned east,
with hopes of finding the fuel they needed
to build their power.
The U.S. presence in
the Middle East started
with one little dot, right here.
But soon, that dot would
expand into a sprawling network
of alliances, covert attacks,
flows of weapons, money,
and the building of innumerable bases,
and eventually turning
into full-on ground wars.
(intriguing music)
This is how the U.S.
stole the Middle East.
(intriguing music)
- Ready and willing to
employ all means necessary.
- Okay, so it's the 1930s
and the U.S. doesn't have
a significant presence
in the Middle East at this point.
But that's about to change,
because there's a company
based in California
that wants to explore
this vast desert for oil.
- [Narrator] 11,000
miles from San Francisco
there lies a primeval desert,
a mass of drifting sand
and sun-baked earth,
one third the size of the United States.
- [Johnny] This was
sort of a risky decision
for the California company
because, first off,
they had no idea if there
was actually any oil here.
- [Narrator] They knew it would mean
sinking into the desert
the money of thousands of stockholders
in a project that might
well end in complete loss.
- [Johnny] And second off,
this desert was a part
of a very hardcore religious kingdom.
- [Narrator] The fact
that Mecca is the source
and the shrine of Islam gives
Saudi Arabia a central place
in the Islamic and,
therefore, the Arab world.
- [Johnny] that was home to
the holiest sites in Islam,
run by a dogmatic royal family
that did not like outsiders,
especially non-believing Westerners.
But even still, the king
of the desert kingdom
eventually gives the
California company permission
to explore almost a
million square kilometers
of this desert looking for oil.
And after a few years, the bet paid off.
And on March 3rd, 1938,
in this little patch of coastal
desert, they struck gold.
Well, actually they struck oil,
but it might as well have been gold.
(kinetic music)
So, throughout the '30s and
'40s, American oil executives,
workers, and their families
started flocking to the Middle East,
establishing the first
significant American presence
in the region.
They set up little cities
around the oil operation
that were little slices of America,
full of the deepest sinful behavior,
like allowing women to drive
and the consumption of alcohol.
- [Narrator] Here is
another American colony,
complete with air-conditioned
houses, two hospitals,
and an outdoor movie theater.
- This is the sort of stuff
that is very off-limits
in Saudi Arabia.
It's literally illegal at this point.
So you have a lot of
Saudis who are not happy
about their government
letting the Americans in
to behave however they want.
But the oil kept flowing,
and soon, the U.S. government
goes to the royal family
and says, "Listen, the oil
is flowing better than ever.
This is awesome.
How about we build a little military base
attached to our little oil city
so that we can, you know, protect you
and protect us and protect
the oil and stuff?"
And the Saudis are like, "Okay.
Having the great Satan come to our country
for oil is one thing,
but letting them set up a full-on
military base on our soil,
(John inhales sharply)
and especially when, like,
everyone in our country
is not happy with their
presence in the first place.
"But," said the royal family,
"all of this oil is really valuable,
and it's really nice, and
we're getting super rich."
So they're like, "Yeah,
sure. Set up the base."
But there was one stipulation
that the Saudis had for the Americans.
"You are not allowed to
literally plant a flag.
No flag poles of the United States.
You cannot put your flag
anywhere on this base.
Instead, you can put a little plaque
on the side of the building
so that your flag is not
literally on our soil."
And that was the deal. And
that's exactly what happened.
The U.S. sets up its
first military operation
in the Middle East in the
form of a landing strip
that is right next to this oil field.
(plane engine roaring)
Okay, so all of this infrastructure
that the Americans were building
required someone to build it.
They needed a construction company.
And there was one construction company
that the Americans really liked
that helped them build their
oil city and their base.
This company was founded and
run by a guy named Mohammed.
Now, listen, do you think
I'm really giving you
the backstory on the construction company
that built the air base in the oil city
just because that's interesting
and I like to talk about construction?
No, this is actually very
relevant to the story,
and you'll see why very soon.
So the Americans and the Saudis are having
this forbidden oil bromance
and it's going really well,
and they are just,
the oil is flowing,
everyone's getting rich.
And meanwhile the rest of the Middle East
is looking at Saudi Arabia
and they're like, "Dude, WTF.
Why are you like in bed with America?
And, like, why are you letting them set up
a landing strip in your country?"
And the Saudi royals are like,
"Do you realize how rich
we're getting right now?
Like if you were in our position,
you would do the same thing, Egypt."
Okay, so it's the 1950s
and let's get back to
Mohammed, the construction guy.
His company, by this point, is thriving.
The American presence in
oil land is just exploding
and he is building all
of the stuff for it.
And so this guy just has a giant business.
And he starts to have children.
Well, in fact, he had a lot of children,
like 54 children because he had 22 wives,
because that is a thing in
Saudi Arabia to this day.
Anyway, the point is one of
Mohammed's sons is named Osama.
(downbeat electronic music)
I told you this was going to be relevant.
Okay, a reminder that Saudi Arabia
is not the entire Middle East.
So, I'm going to leave
the Osama bin Laden
cliffhanger for a moment
to tell you what else was going on
in the Middle East at this time.
Remember that it was the hunt for oil
that brought the U.S. to
Saudi Arabia originally.
But now in the '50s and
'60s, there was a new reason
for the U.S. to think
about the Middle East.
And that reason is because
there's another big superpower
that has nuclear weapons
called the Soviet Union,
who is coming into the region
and saying to everyone,
"Come join team communism."
And the U.S. is like, "Hold my beer."
(dramatic music)
So in addition to oil, the
U.S. is now involved in trying
to not let the Soviet Union
have any power in this region.
Over in Iran, there was a
democratically-elected leader
that the U.S. didn't like.
They thought he was maybe
a little too friendly
with the Soviet Union.
So they worked together with the British
to literally overthrow
the government of Iran
so that they could install
a dictatorial leader
that was more friendly
to the United States.
Little side note here.
The airport that I fly out of here in D.C.
is named after the guy who,
like, gave the go ahead
for this coup in Iran, John Foster Dulles.
So, I'm reminded of the whole
Iran thing every time I fly.
So the U.S. has its oil thing.
It's now involved in trying
to prop up a dictator in Iran.
There's another big thing happening
that brings the U.S. into the region,
which is that the newly
declared State of Israel
is starting to piss off its neighbors
and starting to look to
the U.S. for support.
And the U.S. gladly offers it,
seeing Israel as a friendly
nation in the region
that could be a big
proponent of U.S. interests.
So the U.S. starts to fund
Israel with tons of money
and fighter jets, and all of these things
to help them fight their wars
against their Arab neighbors.
There was a debate happening
in the United States
on whether or not they should
actually do all of this
to support Israel so intensely,
because they knew if they did,
they were going to piss off
all of the neighbors in the Middle East.
And all of the neighbors are
the ones who had the oil.
In the end, the U.S. did
decide to support Israel,
and with that, came a major backlash
from all of these oil-producing countries
in the neighborhood.
- There's a crisis of such proportion
that we probably haven't
even begun to grasp it yet
as far as the country is concerned.
- [Narrator] Scenes like this
are becoming all too common
on both sides of the Atlantic.
But for America, they are more ominous.
They tell the Arabs that their oil weapon
is wounding America,
the country that supports and
supplies their enemy, Israel.
- Eventually, this backlash
against supporting Israel
kind of calmed down.
There was some peace talks.
And anyway, let's get back to Mohammed,
the construction guy, and his son Osama,
because this is where it
really starts to heat up.
We decided to put
together this compilation
of all our Middle East videos
because there are
transformative events happening
in the Middle East right now.
The recent attacks on Iran
from the U.S. and Israel
have reshaped the Middle East
and are doing that right
now as I'm recording this.
And hopefully these videos
are providing some context,
but keeping up with the headlines
is proving to be really difficult
because every source comes
at it with a different angle
and a different bias.
This is why I have
partnered with Ground News.
They are the sponsor of this compilation.
And I've been using Ground
News for over a year now.
They've been a partner of the channel
and I'm really grateful they exist.
Ground News is an app and a website
that allows you to very
quickly and thoroughly
compare thousands of headlines
from all around the world.
It organizes them
and breaks them down by
what their biases are,
their reliability, their factuality,
and even tells you who
these outlets are owned by.
They've been recognized by
the Nobel Peace Center for
Advancing Media Literacy.
And lemme just show you how
this works and why it matters.
Take one event
like the story about
Iran's next supreme leader,
the strikes on Iran,
and the killing of the
Supreme leader in Iran
was covered by over 800 outlets,
all with different angles.
With Ground News, you're
able to quickly compare
and see how the left
and the right are covering it differently.
For example, a left-leaning
outlet emphasizes
the human response from the
Iranian diaspora in Washington.
The right, represented by Fox News,
focuses on the political
backlash of the attack
framing the critics of these
strikes as siding with Iran,
or in their words, "Rooting
for the Ayatollah."
Every news outlet chooses
their narrative. So do we.
This is impossible to avoid.
What Ground News does is
it helps make that visible
by allowing you
to quickly compare lots
of different headlines.
I've used the app for years
and I'm grateful it exists.
It's a kind of comparison
that I can't get elsewhere.
It's an important part
of being a critical consumer of the news.
And it's completely subscriber funded.
There's no, like, rich
billionaire back there
deciding what you see.
It's completely funded by
all of us who pay for it.
If this is interesting to you,
you can get in on the Vantage
Plan, which is the plan I use.
You can get 40% off if you go
to ground.news/johnnyharris.
You can also scan the
QR code here on screen.
You get that 40% off,
it ends up being like five bucks a month
for you to get the whole picture
on the events shaping the world.
With that, let's dive into our next video
about the modern Middle East.
- [Narrator] And it is this
world of religious authority
and deeply-rooted traditions
that is now being challenged
by the wealth of oil
and the Western invasion it has brought.
- So it's now the '70s,
and Mohammed bin Laden,
the construction guy,
is now insanely rich.
His construction company is giant,
his 54 children are also rich,
and his son Osama is growing
up, and he is in his twenties,
and is looking around at
all of this stuff happening
in Iran and in Israel,
and is starting to feel
really uncomfortable
with the notion of his
family being so supportive
of American presence in the Middle East
and his government,
this religious kingdom,
home of Mecca and Medina,
being so okay with the U.S.
so embedded in the Middle
East at this point.
"These are ancient holy lands.
Why is my government and my family
supporting this great
Satan superpower coming in
and becoming so involved
in the Middle East?"
So, Bin Laden sets out on a lifelong quest
to fight back against these superpowers,
not just the U.S. but
also the Soviet Union,
invading the Middle East.
He heads to Afghanistan,
where the Soviet Union
is invading Afghanistan,
trying to take it over.
Bin Laden wants to fight back.
By the way, the same year in Iran,
that dictator that the
U.S. put in gets overthrown
in a giant religious revolution
that gets rid of the old
dictator that the U.S. liked
and puts in a religious government
headed by this guy, Ayatollah Khomeini.
This new government takes a
bunch of Americans hostage
and starts off hating the United States.
And I mean, can you blame them?
If someone overthrew the person I elected,
I would be pretty pissed too.
So anyway, back to Bin Laden.
He arrives to Afghanistan
with a few things.
Number one, a bunch of money.
Remember his family's like super rich.
He also comes with
construction infrastructure
because he's, like, a construction guy.
Like, his family knows construction
and infrastructure building.
But most importantly, he comes
with an obsessive dedication
to fighting back against any superpower
that is invading the Middle East.
So, Osama joins in with
all of these rebel fighters
who are fighting back
against the Soviet Union,
and they fight a long, brutal war.
By the way, the U.S. was
secretly loving this,
loving that the Soviet Union
was getting, like, beat back
by these, like, rebel fighters.
So they end up sending
loads of weapons and money
and support to these fighters,
something that will come back to bite them
a few decades later.
Eventually, Osama and the Afghan fighters
beat back the Soviet Union.
It was 10 brutal years of war,
and by the end, these
fighters were battle hardened.
Osama was now completely
dedicated to his cause
of fighting back against superpowers
who were coming into the Middle East.
So he returns back to Saudi Arabia,
where he starts raising
money and awareness
for his new group
that he started while
he was in Afghanistan.
It's called Al-Qaeda.
And the mission of the
group is to protect Islam
through violently striking
back against big superpowers
coming into the Middle East.
And Saudi Arabia is like,
"(sighs) Osama, like, do
you have to do this, dude?
Do you realize how rich we're getting?"
Like, Saudi princes are living on yachts
in the south of France
and, like, flying in their private jets
and they're like, "Dude, chill.
Like, it's fine. We get it.
We don't like the United States,
but, like, can you, like, maybe chill?
Our partnership with the United States
is actually turning
out to be really great.
And I know, yeah, they're
really into Israel
and they're really bad and everything,
but, like, they buy our oil
and they give us weapons
and we're, like, doing
just fine over here."
Osama doesn't chill,
and the Saudi government
eventually takes away his passport,
not letting him leave,
and told him to hush up
with all the anti-American Holy War talk.
So, Osama finds another plan
to maybe win back the heart of the royals.
(dark music)
Saudi Arabia has a next-door
neighbor named Iraq,
who was run by Saddam Hussein,
who Osama sees as a really bad Muslim,
totally secular and brutal,
and he's just like not a good guy.
Saddam is also cashing in on the oil boom.
He's building big palaces
and statues of himself
all over the country.
Oh yeah, and he also used the oil money
to build a giant army,
like, the fourth biggest in the world.
With this massive army, Saddam decided
that he could maybe
multiply his oil reserves
if he popped down
to invade this little
tiny country of Kuwait,
where there's also loads of oil.
This sort of freaked the Saudis out.
If Saddam with his giant
army could grab Kuwait,
what would stop him from
marching right across this desert
into Saudi Arabia?
So there's this moment that, like,
ugh, it's like the moment of
infamy of this whole thing,
where Osama goes to the
Saudis and he says...
- I volunteer as tribute.
- He doesn't actually say,
"I volunteer in tribute."
That was "Hunger Games."
- I believe we have a volunteer.
- But he effectively says,
"I have me and my battle-hardened men
who, like, can go in
and fight against Saddam
and defend the kingdom."
And the Saudis are like,
"Um, no, we're not gonna,
like, let this ragtag group
of, like, rebel fighters
fight off the fourth-largest
army in the world."
And Osama's like, "Well,
we beat the Soviets.
Like, they're a big army
with nuclear weapons and everything."
And the Saudis are like,
"Yeah, because you hid in the hills,
in caves, in Afghanistan."
Prince Sultan literally told
Bin Laden verbatim, quote,
"There are no caves in Kuwait."
And then he asks them,
"What will you do when he
lobs the missiles at you
with chemical and biological weapons?"
Osama's response, "We will
fight them with our faith."
(sinking music)
And the Saudis are like, "Um, awkward.
Sorry, dude. Like... (scoffs)"
Instead the king met with somebody else
that he thought would
make a much better fit
than Bin Laden and his faith fighters.
(dramatic music)
Dick Cheney had flown to Saudi Arabia
the day after Saddam had invaded Kuwait.
At this point, the
bromance between the U.S.
and Saudi Arabia had cooled a little bit
as Saudi had gotten more and more flak
for being in bed with the U.S.
But even despite this,
he told Cheney to come
with as much force and
as quickly as he could.
And that is exactly what Dick Cheney did.
- Ready and willing to
employ all means necessary.
(explosion booms faintly)
- The U.S. went insane here.
They recruited 37 other countries,
and then they sent more firepower
in terms of ships and bombers and troops
and all this stuff than you
and I could never imagine.
It was insanity. And they
totally crushed Saddam.
Within a few weeks, they
had pushed Saddam back
and completely won over
the hearts of the royals.
The bromance is back in business.
(subdued music)
So, now you have these Saudis
that are beaming at the Americans
for helping them fight off Saddam.
And you have a bunch of
bases that the U.S. set up
to mount this attack.
Way more than before.
The U.S. came with all of
this firepower and manpower
and bases and artillery.
And then they just sort of never left.
Something that really
pissed off a lot of Saudis,
who were very uncomfortable
with U.S. presence to begin with.
But the guy who was most pissed off
than anyone in the Middle
East at this point?
Osama bin Laden,
who had not only been
rejected by his own country,
but then who got chosen instead,
but the great Satan, the United States,
a power that Osama
had built his entire
life fighting against.
So, Osama bin Laden starts to double down
on his original mission.
He leaves Saudi Arabia
and begins coordinating
very precise attacks
that could really only
be coordinated by a guy
who was good at technical
details of a construction company
and who had lots of money to fund it.
He carries out attacks
against the United States
all around the world.
And by the late '90s, he
starts planning the attack
that would change our world forever.
(siren wailing)
(radios chatter)
(audio whines)
(soft dramatic music)
- So, this is just the
first half of the story.
What happens next
is something that we're
all kind of familiar with.
(fanatics chant)
(gunshots chatter)
In fact, I think we're all
still kind of processing
the U.S. presence in the Middle East today
and how that all went down.
But it deserves taking a look at,
and I'm not going to do that right now.
I want to make a separate
video for Iraq and Afghanistan
and Israel and Iran,
and dive into each of these cases
to show how the U.S.
presence in the Middle East
is not just about oil.
In fact, oil is becoming less
and less of a vital aspect
of the U.S. presence
as we have alternative sources
of this sort of energy.
Instead, our presence in
the Middle East has become
a fixture of how we think
about foreign policy
and how we think about the map.
It's become so embedded
in our military doctrine
and in our foreign policy doctrine
that it's proving to be really hard
to think about how we could ever get out.
(soft dramatic music)
One of the most important wars
of the last 50 years is one
that we don't hear about much.
When in 1980, two of the Middle East's
most powerful countries, Iran and Iraq,
waged eight years of
some of the worst trench
and chemical warfare since World War I,
leaving both countries devastated.
This is the war that
fractured the Middle East
into lines that still play out
in nearly every conflict there today.
It set the U.S. and Iraq on a path
that ultimately led to
the American invasion.
And it defined Iran's
often hostile relationship
with the wider world.
This is the Iran-Iraq War.
It's 1979, and Iran is in
the middle of a revolution.
(crowd chanting)
The country is coming off
of decades of being ruled
by the Shah, a king that the U.S. and UK
had installed in the 50s
after covertly overthrowing
Iran's democratically-elected leader.
But after years of The Shah's
corrupt autocratic rule,
a mass uprising violently overthrows him,
creating what becomes an Islamic republic,
headed by an Ayatollah
named Ruhollah Khomeini.
(soft dramatic music)
Khomeini, and a group of
Shia religious scholars,
want to impose fundamentalist
rule on the country
and are hostile to both the Western powers
and the neighboring Soviet Union.
They establish a military force
called the Islamic Revolutionary Guard,
which is meant to protect
their hold on the revolution
and to suppress the other groups
who helped overthrow the Shah.
The U.S. is watching all of this in shock.
Their biggest ally in the
region, and a major oil producer,
has just turned from
friend to fierce enemy.
But the biggest tremors of this revolution
are felt in the rest of the Middle East.
(soft tense music)
Iran sends out radio
broadcasts to Arab countries
like Saudi Arabia,
Lebanon, Kuwait, and Iraq,
calling for people to rise up
and overthrow their own rulers.
They're trying to export their
revolution to their neighbors
to gain new allies in the region.
Neighboring leaders, most
of them Sunni Muslim,
don't like this.
Saudi Arabia's king fears being overthrown
just like the Shah was.
And in Iraq, Saddam Hussein sees
this Shia religious revolution
on his eastern border
and worries that the Shia
majority that he rules over
will rise up against him too.
But he also sees this as an opportunity.
Iran and Iraq have been fighting
over this border territory for years.
This waterway is a critical
access point to the Persian Gulf
where both countries export their oil
to the rest of the world.
In a treaty between the two back in 1975,
Saddam had to give up full
control of this waterway,
as well as access to oil-rich
regions in what was now Iran.
Saddam hates this treaty
and is considering taking
the waterway back by force.
The Iranian Revolution
has left the country weak and fractured.
Khomeini and his revolutionary guard
are still fighting other
political factions for control.
The Iranian military,
which used to be funded
and trained by the United
States, is now weak,
its leaders having been jailed
or executed after the revolution.
Iran's military would
normally be able to crush Iraq
in an invasion, but maybe not anymore.
Saddam sees this as an opportunity
to weaken a major rival.
Saddam is also riding on a delusion
that he himself is going
to unify the Arab world
under his leadership.
If he invades Iran,
maybe the rest of the Middle
East will rally behind him
against this new common enemy.
He thinks it'll be a quick victory.
So in September of 1980,
he decides to prepare 10,000 Iraqi troops
to cross the border to invade Iran.
(soft dramatic music)
(engine rumbling)
What's about to happen here
isn't just the start of a new war.
(guns boom)
Saddam is kicking off a dynamic
that will dominate the Middle
East for more than 40 years,
the fight between revolutionary
change and status quo power.
(subdued music)
The war officially starts
when Saddam sends his
air force over the border
in a surprise attack on Iranian air bases.
His 10,000 soldiers cross
from Basra into Southern Iran.
Further north, Saddam opens a second front
to seize strategically-located
border towns
and put pressure on his enemy.
These air attacks mostly fail,
and Iran responds with
airstrikes of their own
into Iraqi territory
hitting oil facilities.
Iran still has sophisticated jets
that the United States had
given the previous regime.
This gives them an edge in the air.
(bombs booming)
The war quickly sucks in
the rest of the region.
Israel is among the first.
It wants to keep these
two adversaries occupied,
fighting with each other,
keeping both sides weak.
So almost immediately,
Israel secretly sells
supplies and parts to Iran.
This helps the Iranian Air
Force keep planes in the air.
Now, Iran and Israel are not friends,
but Israel sees Iraq as
a greater threat here.
So they're willing to support.
Iran needs to get its military organized
if they're gonna fight this war.
So they release military officers
that they had jailed
during the revolution.
War tends to unify a nation,
and in this case, the
fractured country of Iran
is unifying around Iraq's invasion,
creating this irony that Saddam is the one
who actually cements
Khomeini's hold on power.
Saudi Arabia and Kuwait also step in here,
giving billions of dollars
to fund Iraq's war efforts.
They want to weaken Iran and
turn back its revolution.
The Middle East is now dividing
between, on one side,
Arab states who are ruled
by aging, Sunni monarchies
and strongmen who fear change,
and on the other side, a
Shia Iran bent on revolution,
on remaking the region in its image.
China is also watching this war.
They say they will
maintain strict neutrality,
but they take the
opportunity to sell weapons
to both sides of the conflict.
They eventually become Iran's
top supplier of weapons.
(subdued music)
For most of 1981, the two
armies are in a stalemate,
with Iraq holding small
but important stretches
of border territory.
The global powers see this stalemate
and try to negotiate a ceasefire,
hoping that this conflict
that threatens so much
of the global oil supply
will end soon.
What they don't know
is that this is really just the beginning.
Saddam agrees to the ceasefire,
but Khomeini does not.
This war has become so
useful to his goals,
unifying the country and
keeping the military occupied
so that it doesn't become
a rival to his power.
Khomeini needs the war to continue.
So Iran demands that
Saddam Hussein step down.
They say the war will continue
until his rule is ended.
Saddam, of course, refuses.
So Iran goes on the offensive.
Their forces are now organized.
Their officers have been freed from jail,
and they're able to
recapture the territory
that Saddam had taken,
even pushing into Iraq.
Saddam's hopes of a quick victory
and a gain of some valuable
territory are now dead.
So he turns to the
United States for support
and the U.S. agrees to help.
They hope to weaken Iran
and its call for anti-American
Islamic revolution
across the region.
So the U.S. starts giving
Saddam intelligence
and satellite imagery on
Iranian troop movement.
Iraq also gets another big
backer, the Soviet Union.
The Soviets are at war in
neighboring Afghanistan
trying to suppress another
religious uprising,
but they also have allies in this region.
So over the course of the war,
the Soviets become a top
supplier of weapons to Iraq.
Now remember the situation
between these two.
It's a tense moment in the Cold War,
and the United States and Soviet Union
are suddenly supporting the same side
of this Middle East conflict,
both backing the country
that will support the status
quo, nothing changing,
allowing their great power
struggle to continue as it has.
But by the summer of 1982,
Iran is now pushing into Iraqi territory,
much of their campaign
focused on the city of Basra.
If Iran can take Basra,
it will cut off Iraq
from the Persian Gulf,
preventing them from
shipping out their oil.
Iraqi forces are outnumbered
here, so they start to dig in
and build trenches, erecting
barbed wire barriers,
planting landmines, and
surrounding the city
to stop Iran from taking it.
The fighting starts to resemble
the brutal warfare of World War I,
waves of artillery strikes,
and the Iranian military
resorting to human wave attacks
where thousands of boys and
men charge over open fields
leading to huge numbers of casualties.
Iran is not successful in taking the city,
but this attack does weaken Saddam,
showing that he's vulnerable.
And this is where we
need to look to the north
to talk about the Kurds.
(subdued music)
The Kurds are a minority
group in the north of Iraq.
They've been long suppressed
by Saddam Hussein,
and they see this moment as an opportunity
to break away from Iraq
to make their own country.
So Kurdish forces start
fighting with the Iraqi army,
taking towns and villages.
So now Saddam is fighting
two different armies,
one of which lives in his own country.
Iran starts sending support to the Kurds
who have a presence in this mountainous,
oil-rich part of Iraq.
If the Kurds can hold it
and keep Saddam's regime
away from all of this oil,
it would have a major effect on this war.
This is a big deal for Saddam,
and he switches tactics
to make sure he can
control this northern area.
He escalates by using chemical weapons
against the Kurds as well as the Iranians.
Shells filled with mustard gas,
weapons that cause extreme
burning and blindness,
a weapon that is illegal
under international law,
but even still, the global powers
who are supporting him
mostly look the other way.
The U.S. starts sending
technology and money to Saddam,
even restoring official
diplomatic ties with Iraq.
This allows Iraq to buy
technology from the United States
that helps them develop
their weapons programs,
including the horrific
chemical and biological weapons
that he will soon be
using on the battlefield.
They need him to keep fighting
because this war has changed.
It went from protecting
Saddam from revolution
to now using Saddam to weaken Iran.
So they keep supporting him,
showing him that he can
use chemical weapons
without being punished.
The chemical attacks help
push back Iranian forces,
and the war reaches a new stalemate.
1984 is the year that the oil
war begins in this conflict.
Iraq starts attacking Iranian oil tankers
in the Persian Gulf using
new jets provided by France,
a new entrant to this conflict.
Saddam warns that he'll
also attack any ship
going into Iranian ports.
Iran retaliates by attacking oil tankers
carrying Iraq's oil.
The oil that the entire globe relies on
is now at the center of this
increasingly brutal conflict.
Hundreds of commercial ships
are attacked by both sides,
resulting in the death of
over 400 civilian sailors.
The U.S. has to send in two frigates
and a guided missile destroyer
into the Persian Gulf
to escort U.S. ships,
hoping that their presence
will stop these attacks.
Meanwhile, Iran is making
progress on the ground,
slowly taking territory from Iraq
and continuing attacks on
the vital port city of Basra.
(soft grim music)
It's 1985 and Saddam is about
to escalate to a new extreme.
He starts shooting
missiles and dropping bombs
on Iranian cities all over the country,
including the capitol.
This kills 16,000 people
and leaves many homeless.
Iran responds, striking Iraqi cities,
firing these massive missiles,
primarily at the capital of Baghdad.
These strikes hit civilian targets
like a school and a bus station
with hundreds of casualties.
Civilians on both sides are
now caught in the crossfire
of this brutally escalating war.
Their cities and their homes
are not safe, so many flee.
These events leave an
entire generation scarred
by the trauma of war and a
disdain for the outside powers
that have ripped their country apart.
And speaking of outside powers,
this is when the U.S.
starts double dealing.
They start selling missiles to Iran,
which gives Iran an edge
against Iraqi forces
who the U.S. is also supporting.
Behind all this is
President Ronald Reagan,
who wants to use the money from this deal
to fund an anti-communist
militia group in Nicaragua.
It's all supposed to be a secret,
but will eventually come out
and be known as the Iran-Contra scandal.
Meanwhile, Kuwait is asking
the U.S. to be more aggressive
to protect their oil tankers.
Iranian attacks on their ships
have started to take a toll.
The U.S. is getting more
involved in the war.
Their presence in the
Persian Gulf is growing.
They start putting American
flags on Kuwaiti tankers
to deter Iran from attacking them.
And then in March of 1988,
Iran partners with the Kurdish fighters
to take over the Iraqi town of Halabja.
The Kurds know that this
is going to set Saddam off,
and they brace themselves
for a brutal retaliation.
But what comes next
is worse than anyone
could have prepared for.
The Iraqi army drops bombs
and artillery shells
containing deadly chemicals,
blanketing the entire town
with a cloud of deadly gas
that sinks into homes
and buildings and the underground shelters
where many were hiding for protection.
It's a brutal attack that
kills over 5,000 Iraqi Kurds,
mostly unarmed civilians.
And it was a part of a broader campaign
that Saddam was now waging
to wipe out the Kurdish people entirely.
He now had what he believed
was a justification.
So the Iraqi Army starts
going village to village,
dropping chemical weapons on civilians
and executing any survivors.
This resulted in an estimated
50 to 100,000 deaths
in what has now been deemed as a genocide,
one of the many war crimes
committed by Saddam Hussein.
The U.S. knows this is happening,
and yet, according to
now-public documents,
the official government line
was to turn a blind eye,
to blame everything on Iran.
Saddam's horrific war crimes
project a new fear onto
the civilians in Iran
who now worry that a missile
loaded with deadly gas
could land on their cities.
Many flee to take
shelter in the mountains.
And by now, after eight
years of devastating war,
Iran's economy and social order is frayed.
Their leader, Ayatollah Khomeini,
is feeling the pressure to end this war.
More than a million lives
have been lost in this war.
All sides are looking for a way out.
And the UN Security Council
is pressuring the parties
to accept a ceasefire.
Then in July of 1988, a U.S.
ship in the Persian Gulf
shoots down an Iranian passenger jet,
(soft tense music)
killing all 290 civilians on board.
The U.S. shakes it off as
an unfortunate accident,
saying that they mistook the airliner
for a hostile F-16 fighter jet.
They pay compensation to
the victim's families,
and President Reagan sends
a letter apologizing,
but the government never
formally apologizes.
And the captain of the ship who did this
later received a medal which
fed a deep suspicion in Iran
that this attack was deliberate,
that it was a scheme to coerce
them into accepting peace.
Fear of more American attacks,
along with a new offensive by Iraq,
pushes the Iranian forces to
withdraw from the country,
and both sides finally accept a ceasefire.
(subdued music)
The war is finally over,
and after all of this,
the borders were unchanged
from before the fighting.
But in some ways, this was
really just the first round
in a larger conflict that has
continued through to today,
a war for the future of the Middle East,
one that the United States
is deeply involved in
but that most expresses
itself as a cold war
between Saudi Arabia and Iran,
who now fuel civil wars around the region
in Lebanon, Syria, and Yemen,
backing their own proxy fighters
and making these conflicts worse.
But another major takeaway
here is that this war
defined Iran's relationship
to the rest of the world,
especially the United States.
Iranian hardliners came to
feel confirmed in their belief
that they could never
trust an outside world
bent on Iran's destruction
and seemingly unconstrained
in their violence,
leading some leaders to conclude
that only nuclear weapons
could stave off disaster from the outside.
Saddam Hussein's Iraq
emerged battered by this war,
humiliated by this failure against Iran.
He faced growing internal
resistance from his people,
which he suppressed with
more and more violence.
He also came out of
this with huge war debts
to Kuwait and Saudi Arabia.
Angry that his allies
had billed him to fight
a war on their behalf,
a few years later, Saddam
invades Kuwait seeking its oil,
taking the spoils that
he felt he was owed.
And this is when his one-time
backer, the United States,
quickly turns against him,
expelling him from Kuwait
and beating him back in
a swift 43-day victory,
cutting him off from the world economy
and turning him into a pariah, an enemy.
A decade after Saddam had
gassed his own people,
the U.S. finally blamed him for it,
turning it into a byword for his cruelty
and the centerpiece for their
demand that he step down.
A few years later, George W. Bush
would cite these weapons
of mass destructions,
the ones that he would never find,
as a reason to invade the
country to topple Saddam.
Bush's war room was filled
with the same officials
who had covered for Saddam
and his war crimes in the first place,
and making it so crystal clear
that, even though this war
between Iran and Iraq ended decades ago,
the Middle East we see today
is built off of what happened
during those eight brutal years.
Before we go into the next
video, I just want to remind you
that this is all made possible
because of Ground News,
the sponsor of this compilation.
Ground News helps me do these deep dives
by helping me compare lots of headlines
and revealing the different biases
and reliability of the
facts in those headlines.
You can go to ground.news/johnnyharris
to get 40% off their Vantage Plan
and start comparing headlines
and seeing clearly into the
news that you're consuming.
(dramatic music)
(keyboard clicking)
In the summer of 2002,
the Director of the British
Intelligence Agency, MI6,
Richard Dearlove, traveled
to Washington D.C.
to meet with the Director
of the CIA, George Tenet.
The topic of the meeting was Iraq
and its leader, Saddam Hussein.
In the meeting,
the CIA director shared
classified information
with his British counterpart,
who then traveled back to
London to 10 Downing Street,
the home of the Prime
Minister, Tony Blair.
Dearlove told his Prime
Minister everything
about what was really
happening behind the scenes
in the United States,
how the U.S. was planning to
invade Iraq no matter what.
It was a highly classified meeting
but notes were taken and
classified and put into a memo.
That memo was later leaked
to British author and
journalist, Michael Smith,
who published it in 2005
and that's what we're looking at,
a secret meeting and the memo it produced,
meant only for the eyes
of top British officials.
It was an explosive leak.
What we see is that Dearlove
tells his Prime Minister
everything he heard in
Washington a few days earlier,
and that this was a very different story
than the one the Bush administration
was telling to the public,
that an American invasion was inevitable,
that Bush's people were fixated
on removing Saddam Hussein
from power, no matter what,
and that the U.S. government
was blatantly cooking up intel and facts
to help sell their invasion.
This document shows us how
power really works in our world,
how a small group of people
decided to topple a dictator,
to occupy a country,
and then invented a story
to support their plan.
It was a false story,
but it helped them sell a horrifying war.
It's a story that is revealed in detail
by the Downing Street memo.
(dramatic music continues)
- States like these
constitute an axis of evil.
One last chance to avoid war.
And the entire world will know
that we will take whatever
actions necessary.
On September the 11th, enemies of freedom
committed an act of war
against our country.
The United States
military has begun strikes
against Al-Qaeda terrorist
training camps in Afghanistan.
- [Johnny] Let's start by looking
at another document from the fall of 2001
when Deputy Secretary of
Defense Paul Wolfowitz
created this memo for his
boss, Donald Rumsfeld,
the Secretary of Defense.
This was just 10 weeks after the attacks
that changed the course of history
but this document wasn't about that.
It was about Iraq,
a country that had
nothing to do with 9/11.
Rumsfeld reviewed the document
before meeting with an army general.
He marked it up with his notes,
giving us insight into
what the Secretary of
Defense of the United States
was really thinking about after 9/11,
how this group of military leaders
were set on, quote, "building momentum"
to topple Iraq's dictator, Saddam Hussein,
to decapitate the government,
a government that was no
longer useful to them.
Saddam Hussein had been a useful client
to the United States,
especially in the '80s
when he was waging a war against Iran,
an enemy of the United States.
But those days were now over.
Saddam had turned into just
a troublemaker in the region,
creating instability that could threaten
the U.S.' easy access to oil.
- Two hours ago, allied
air forces began an attack
on military targets in Iraq and Kuwait.
This conflict started August 2nd
when the dictator of Iraq
invaded a small and helpless neighbor.
- [Johnny] And in many
ways, Iraq was an old mess
in need of cleaning up,
a mess that Bush Senior
had failed to resolve
during the first Gulf War.
Iraq was supposed to disarm
itself after that war
but had kicked out the UN
weapons inspector teams.
(brooding music)
But that wasn't the main
reason why, right after 9/11,
these guys were talking
about invading Iraq.
A bigger reason is that
these leaders wanted
to remind the world who
the global superpower was.
They needed to
after being brutally
attacked on their own soil.
A non-U.S.-friendly regime, like Iraq,
couldn't be allowed to
stand in a post 9/11 world,
or in the words of Rumsfeld himself,
hours after the towers fell,
quote, "We need to bomb something else
to show that we're big and strong
and not gonna be pushed around."
Iraq and its leader was
that something else.
And now, Bush and his advisors
were looking at a plan
to make it a reality.
But how to start the war?
Could they tie Saddam Hussein
to something that Americans
feared, like 9/11 or anthrax?
Or could they tell a story
about weapons of mass destruction?
What other countries could they bring in
to support their invasion?
And, of course, the most
important consideration,
Rumsfeld jots it here at the end,
they would need an influence campaign,
they would need to sell the war.
And when should they begin?
How about right away?
(intense music)
- Iraq continues to flaunt his hostility
toward America and to support terror.
- [Johnny] Three months later,
the President was telling the world
that Iraq was one of a
group of evil countries
that the U.S. must oppose
in the global fight against good and evil.
- States like these
constitute an axis of evil.
The price of indifference
would be catastrophic.
- [Johnny] By the summer of 2002,
this idea that Bush's advisors
had scratched down after 9/11
was developing into an official policy.
That handwritten influence campaign
to sell the war was now in full swing.
- There is no doubt that Saddam Hussein
now has weapons of mass destruction.
- The Iraqi regime has been free
to pursue the development of
weapons of mass destruction.
- We know they have weapons
of mass destruction,
there isn't any debate about it.
- [Johnny] And this is
exactly what the head of MI6
told Prime Minister
Tony Blair at his house
in the summer of 2002
after meeting with the CIA in Washington.
It's what we see in
the Downing Street memo
that there was a perceptible
shift in attitude in Washington
and that the U.S. invasion of Iraq
was now seen as inevitable
and that they were now fixing intelligence
around a decision that
they had already made,
and that the U.S. wasn't really planning
to work with the UN.
They didn't want weapons inspections
or getting UN approval
for a military force.
And crucially, the head of the
MI6 tells the Prime Minister
that these Bush people
aren't really thinking much
about the aftermath of such an invasion.
- What is inevitable is not regime change,
it is disarmament of
weapons of mass destruction.
(subdued music)
- [Johnny] This memo wasn't supposed
to be seen by anyone but just a few,
and that's why we can learn from it.
It serves as one of the most
potent pieces of evidence
that the Bush administration
was maneuvering two
very different stories.
Their private story about the need
to remove a dictator
to project U.S. power,
which was in stark contrast
to the public story
that they had to tell
to sell the invasion,
their influence campaign.
- Any country on the face of the earth
with an active intelligence program
knows that Iraq has weapons
of mass destruction.
- [Johnny] Because they knew
that if they were really
gonna sell this war,
they would need to convince
not only the American public
but also Congress and at least partially,
the international community.
What we learned in the Downing Street memo
is that they had settled
on two main focus points for their story,
that Iraq has weapons of mass destruction
and that they're also working
with the masterminds of 9/11.
Not long after this meeting
between MI6 and the CIA,
Bush and his allies ramp
up their influence campaign
to sell their war.
- We've learned that Iraq
has trained Al-Qaeda members
in bomb making, poisons, and deadly gases.
- [Johnny] The sales pitches
to the American people
for an invasion of Iraq were
made with absolute certainty.
Certainty that Iraq had WMDs.
- He had agreed, and the UN had agreed,
that he would not have a WMD program.
We know he does have one.
- [Johnny] Certainty that
they wanted to use them
against Americans and American allies.
- Simply stated, there is no doubt
that Saddam Hussein now has
weapons of mass destruction,
that he is amassing them
to use against our friends,
against our allies, and against us.
- [Johnny] Certainty that
Iraq was harboring terrorists.
- An Al-Qaeda terrorist
escaped from Afghanistan
and are known to be in Iraq.
- [Johnny] And certainty that Iraq
was working on obtaining nuclear weapons.
- And Iraq's state-controlled media
has reported numerous meetings
between Saddam Hussein and
his nuclear scientists,
leaving little doubt
about his continued
appetite for these weapons.
- [Johnny] And these
speeches were working.
By the fall of 2002,
Americans were in favor
of an invasion of Iraq by
just a narrow majority.
But there was just one problem,
that all of these statements were lies.
(moody music)
Indeed, this was already known
in the secret rooms of Downing Street
that the U.S. was fixing
their facts and their intel
to match their already-made decision.
Iraq's supposed links to Al-Qaeda
were based on one interrogation of a guy
whose testimony lacked,
quote, "specific details"
and who was intentionally lying about it
to mislead his interrogators.
Bush and his allies knew this,
it was clearly documented
back in February of 2002,
and yet publicly,
the scary story about
Al-Qaeda being in Iraq
continued to be sold
by Bush and his people.
- The Iraqi regime has
plotted to develop anthrax,
nerve gas, and nuclear
weapons for over a decade.
- [Johnny] The case for weapons
of mass destruction in Iraq
was equally thin and
senior officials knew it.
Like in September, 2002,
when Donald Rumsfeld received this report
from the Joint Chiefs
assessing what real
evidence there actually was
for WMD in Iraq.
The report is shockingly honest
and it says that the conclusion
that Saddam has WMD, quote,
"Relied heavily on analytic
assumptions and judgments
rather than hard evidence."
That's word salad for it was
speculation and conjecture.
The report goes on to say
that they didn't have anything solid
on nuclear weapons-related facilities,
and concludes that they
don't know of any facilities
where Saddam may be producing
or testing biological weapons.
And so, we know now that
they had almost no evidence
for their story about why
the U.S. should invade Iraq.
And yet even knowing this,
they kept selling the same story,
convincing the American people.
- There's no doubt in my mind
he wants to have a nuclear weapon
and he's got some capacity.
- Wherever threats are
forming against our country,
we will respond.
- [Johnny] But they couldn't
go on like this forever.
They knew that if they were
really gonna sell this war,
they were going to need to
show real convincing evidence,
not to the people, but to Congress.
And this is where we get another instance
of fixing the intelligence
to fit the policy.
It came in September, 2002,
when President Bush asked Congress
to give him the authority to invade Iraq.
In response, Senate leaders requested
an immediate National
Intelligence Estimate,
which is a report from the
entire intelligence community
meant to help Congress
make informed decisions.
This could be really bad
for Bush and his allies.
So he and the CIA get hard at work
pulling together a report
that fits their story,
intelligence to back up
all their public statements and speeches.
They come out with this
highly redacted report
that they deliver in October of 2002.
The report makes some very strong claims.
They claim that Iraq has
been building more WMD,
that they have chemical
and biological weapons,
and that they will have a nuclear
weapon during this decade.
And to congressional leaders,
this appeared rock solid.
Here was the entire intelligence community
coming together saying that
Iraq had horrific weapons
and that they wanted to get more.
- Saddam Hussein has composed
a scarlet chapter of terror.
Our only responsible option
is to confront this threat
before Americans die.
- There is no such thing as
a Democrat or Republican war.
- [Johnny] So in that same month,
based on this report and all
of these public speeches,
Congress gives the green light for war.
(heart beat thumping)
(distressing music)
But this National Intelligence
Estimate was deeply flawed.
It was a perfect example
of the fixed intelligence
described in the Downing Street memo.
It was put together in less
than a month, totally rushed.
The report had been plagued by groupthink
and directed by political pressure
with the Bush administration
pushing analysts
to deliver a report that
matched their conclusions
that they had already
come to months earlier.
And they did this using
very old intelligence.
The CIA hadn't had any human
assets on the ground for years,
so their report
wasn't even based off
of anything after 1998.
But it didn't matter,
Bush and his allies had
successfully sold the war
to Congress and the American people.
But there was one last hurdle.
It was the international community,
which would mean they would
have to face the UN process
that they apparently had no patience for.
- Iraq has answered a decade of UN demands
with a decade of defiance.
- [Johnny] So it's November, 2002,
and in response to the rising tensions
between Iraq and the U.S.,
the UN Security Council
passes this resolution, 1441.
It was a measure that
was meant to give Iraq
a final opportunity to comply
with weapons inspections
to show the world that
they had fully disarmed
and had no weapons of mass destruction.
Bush and his allies saw
this as an opportunity,
if they could somehow show
that Iraq wasn't complying with
this new inspection process,
this resolution implied
that they would be justified
in invading the country.
Their long-desired war would be on.
But they had a problem,
which is that Iraq and Saddam Hussein
were complying with the
weapons inspections.
Over the course of four months,
UN weapons inspectors searched
Iraq from top to bottom.
They were led by Hans Blix,
the former Head of the
International Atomic Energy Agency.
They conducted over 900
inspections at over 500 locations
and they didn't find anything,
no WMD, no biological weapons,
no nuclear weapons programs.
- Iraq has, on the whole,
cooperated rather well.
Access has been provided
to all sites we have wanted to inspect,
universities, military bases,
presidential sites,
and private residences.
- [Johnny] Hans Blix did find two things
that were important.
First, they did find
some ballistic missiles
that the UN says have an effective range
that makes them illegal,
so they would need to
be destroyed by Iraq.
And second, there were
some chemical weapons
that the Iraqi regime said
cannot be accounted for.
But Blix insists that this does not mean
that they have these weapons,
it just means that they need more time
to work out the accounting situation.
But this error was exactly
what the Bush circle needed
to justify their invasion.
- [UN Announcer] I call now
on the distinguished Secretary of State
of the United States of America.
- [Johnny] They sent their
most respected cabinet member
to the UN, Secretary
of State, Colin Powell.
He came equipped with photos
of what he says are
mobile weapons facilities.
- Saddam Hussein and his regime
are concealing their efforts
to produce more weapons
of mass destruction.
- [Johnny] He plays
tapes that he says prove
that the Iraqis are hiding their weapons.
- [Powell] We evacuated
everything to make sure
it was not around when
the inspectors showed up.
- [Johnny] And then he says
that this is solid evidence
that shows that Iraq is
violating the UN resolution
that told them to disarm.
This whole thing contradicts
what the UN weapons inspectors
had found in their hundreds
and hundreds of inspections.
They bulldozed the process,
and say they have justification to invade.
- My colleagues, we have an obligation
to see that our resolutions
are complied with.
- They've got the
American public on board,
they've got Congress on board,
and now the UK is in lockstep.
- This is the time for this house
to show that we will stand up
for what we know to be right,
to show that we will confront
the tyrannies and
dictatorships and terrorists
who put our way of life at risk.
- [Johnny] The Bush administration
abandons the UN process,
and that March, his people do
what they set out to do 18 months earlier,
when they were looking
for something else to bomb
(missile roars)
to show who's really in
charge on the world stage.
- My fellow citizens,
American and coalition forces
are in the early stages
of military operations to
disarm Iraq, to free its people,
and to defend the world from grave danger.
America faces an enemy that has no regard
for conventions of war
or rules of morality.
(tense music)
(explosion booming)
(gunshots pop)
- [Johnny] Bush's war took the life
of an estimated half million Iraqis,
and thousands more who
fought for their country.
And over the course of
a decade occupying Iraq,
no weapons were found,
no nuclear facilities,
no mobile weapons labs.
In fact, it seemed like Iraq
had dismantled its nuclear
program back in 1991,
and the rest of its chemical
and biological weapons
just a few years later.
After the invasion,
the U.S. never allowed the UN inspectors
back into the country to
help with their search.
The U.S. would never find a way
to link the Iraqi regime
to Al-Qaeda or to anthrax.
Colin Powell, the Secretary of State,
who played a major role
in selling this war
to the international community
would later say that he regrets his part
in starting the war.
- I deeply regret that some
of the information I presented
which was multi-source was wrong.
- [Johnny] Hans Blix, the
Chief Weapons Inspector
for the UN, would comment later that year
that, "It is sort of fascinating
that you can have 100% certainty
about weapons of mass destruction
and zero certainty about where they are."
We may never know what was in the heart
and minds of these senior leaders,
whether they truly
believed their own lies,
whether they felt justified
in the choices they made.
But what we can learn from this story
is how these leaders behaved
when they thought no one was watching,
when they thought they could tell
a compelling story to the public
while having a totally
different set of motivations.
And how, with enough fear
and enough deception,
you can lead an entire society
into an unprovoked war,
changing the course of
history in the process.
(subdued music)
Up in the Zagros Mountains
have long lived a people called the Kurds.
They're a people with a
centuries long history
of fighting back against invaders
who have crossed through their
lands, resisting conquest
in the name of defending their
shared cultural identity.
Some living as nomads,
a people with no friends
but these mountains.
Eventually the Ottoman Empire
did take over all of this
territory, but even then,
the Kurds maintained
large amounts of autonomy
and freedom in their land.
Then came World War I
when the European powers
defeated the Ottoman Empire
and conquered all of this.
The winners got together
and discussed how they would
carve it up between them.
If you look back at old European maps,
you'll see that all of this
area would be labeled Kurdistan,
an area where the Kurdish people lived
and had some self-rule.
So while drawing these lines,
the British wanted to mark all
of this as Kurdish territory,
paving away for an independent
country for the Kurds,
but the new leader of
Turkey opposed this plan.
He didn't wanna give all this land
and resources to the Kurds.
So he pushed the European
forces out of Turkey.
They gave up on this plan to
give the Kurds their own land.
And in the end, instead of
drawing borders around the Kurds,
the Europeans drew borders through them.
What could have been Kurdistan
was now five different territories,
the Kurds split between them.
(inquisitive music)
But at first these were
just lines on a map
and the Kurds continued to
move through this region.
Eventually the Europeans left,
and these became independent countries
with leaders who wanted to
consolidate and centralize power.
So these lines hardened,
restricting the Kurds' movement
and their livelihood in this region.
But even still, across this region,
the Kurds didn't give up on their idea
of someday gaining
independence, self-rule,
or maybe even a country of their own.
(foreboding music)
Throughout the 1900s,
the Kurds in each of these new countries
took different approaches
to fight for an independent Kurdish state.
Some Kurds would use politics,
others would use violence.
The early uprisings were
crushed by the leaders
of these new countries who
saw the Kurds as a threat
to their efforts to unify their country
around a common language and culture.
Like in Iran, where the Kurds
had some political rights,
but they fought for more.
They wanted autonomy and independence.
The government of Iran
wouldn't have any of this.
They would crack down with
violence on the Kurds,
often supported by Western powers.
By the 1970s, Iran was
going through a revolution
and the Kurds tried again to rise up,
but this new regime had no tolerance
for a group that would
challenge the leadership
of the ruling religious leader.
So once again, they were put down.
Over in Iraq, Kurdish fighters fought hard
against the government
throughout the 20th century,
until the 1970s, when
this new regime came in
and made a deal with the Kurds,
saying that they would be
recognized as an ethnic group
and would be guaranteed
political representation.
It seemed like a huge deal for the Kurds,
but it turned out to be a false promise.
The Iraqi regime, now
led by Saddam Hussein,
would continue to repress the Kurds,
eventually dropping
deadly chemical weapons
on Kurdish towns in Iraq,
systematically killing
thousands of Kurdish civilians
in a genocide supported
by American-made supplies
that were sold to Saddam.
Over in Syria, the Kurds
were treated decently
under the French-controlled government.
(subdued music)
They were citizens and had some rights.
But after the French left in the 40s,
the regimes that came
after oppressed the Kurds,
and by the 1970s,
the Syrian government was
arresting and deporting them,
taking their land and giving it to Arabs.
In total, the Syrian government
would remove 140,000
Kurds from the country.
Decades later, Syria and the United States
would both find the Kurds in Syria useful
for their political goals.
But first, let's talk about Turkey.
(inquisitive music)
There's more Kurdish people
here than in any other country.
The same government
that had fought against
a Kurdish state early on
continued to oppress the Kurds,
denying them citizenship,
outlawing their language,
and keeping them out of politics,
all with the goal of wiping
out their culture from Turkey
as a part of this Turkification campaign,
which tried to unify
Turkey under one culture,
targeting the Kurds and
other ethnic minorities.
Some Kurds fought back against
this in the early years,
but were quickly crushed
by the Turkish state,
(explosions boom)
leading to the creation of
an armed insurgent group
with communist ideology.
They're called the Kurdish
Workers Party, or PKK,
and it would become one of
the biggest Turkish resistance movements.
The PKK would use violence
like suicide bombings
and improvised explosives,
as well as youth militia fighters
against the Turkish government,
tactics that they say are the only way
to fight back against such oppression.
And as a result, Turkey
and most Western powers
consider the PKK a terrorist group.
So that's how the Kurds
in these four countries
became locked in a conflict
with their governments.
They all have different struggles,
but they're all unified by the dream
of some version of Kurdish independence.
(subdued music)
But it doesn't take long for these regimes
to see that they could use the
Kurds as a tool, as a weapon.
One of the earliest examples of this
happens at the end of World War II
when the Soviet Union sees
an opportunity to gain land
and access to oil by supplying
and arming the Kurds in Iran,
allowing them to rise up
against the government
and declare their own country
supported by the Soviet Union.
But it didn't work.
The U.S. pressures the Soviets to leave,
and now without support,
the government of Iran,
which is backed by the U.S. and UK,
go on to crush this movement
of Kurds in their country.
The Kurds are back to being
repressed by the government.
In the 1980s, Syria uses the Kurds
as a weapon against its rival Turkey
when it allows the PKK to
start operating within Syria,
giving them money and weapons
so that they can hurt Turkey.
Syria is doing this in
spite of having spent years
removing hundreds of thousands of Kurds
from its own country.
This escalates the
conflict between these two,
and Turkey threatens to invade Syria.
So Syria backs down and kicks the PKK out
to avoid being invaded,
showing once again how the
Kurds' willingness to fight
can easily become a pawn in
the geopolitics of the region,
discarded once they aren't useful anymore.
In the 1980s, Iran and
Iraq both used the Kurds
at the same time as a
weapon to hurt each other,
even as both are cracking down on Kurds
in their own country.
Saddam Hussein funds and
arms the Kurds in Iran,
while Iran funds the
Kurds in northern Iraq,
both sides hoping to
spark a Kurdish uprising
that will distract and weaken their enemy.
In Iraq, Saddam Hussein retaliates
against the Kurds in his country
with that genocidal chemical
attack we talked about earlier
that killed at least 50,000 Kurdish people
and probably much more.
Once again, the Kurdish
dream of independence
was used by outsiders as a weapon,
and the Kurdish people
paid heavily for it.
(intense music)
The U.S. would get
involved when in the '90s
they would come to this region
fighting against Saddam
Hussein for the first time.
The U.S. rallies the Kurds,
calling for them to overthrow Saddam.
George Bush Sr. literally
calls them to action
with television and radio
broadcasts throughout the country.
- That the Iraqi people
should put him aside,
and that would facilitate the resolution
of all these problems that exist
and certainly would facilitate
the acceptance of Iraq
back into the family of
peace-loving nations.
- [Johnny] And it seems to work.
It sparks an uprising that
looks successful at first.
The U.S. had instigated this uprising,
and they have forces in the region
that they could send to support the Kurds,
but they do nothing.
This allows Saddam to regather his forces
and crush this coup and to
increase this oppression,
ensuring that nothing like
this ever happens again.
Now, the U.S. and UK do eventually step in
to create this no-fly zone
meant to protect the Kurds in the north
and the Shiites in the south.
This gives the Kurds some
autonomy over their region
and protects them from further
airstrikes by the Iraqi Army.
Soon the U.S. is back in Iraq.
It's 2003, and the Bush
administration decides to invade
and remove Saddam from power.
The Kurds in Iraq hope that the
U.S. presence in this region
will mean finally they
will get their own state,
they will be independent.
They join the U.S. in
fighting against Saddam
and his loyalists, battling insurgents,
and later against ISIS.
(gunshots crackle)
The Kurds would even go on to hold a vote,
showing that 92% of the population
was in favor of independence,
but the U.S. won't support this,
worried that it might
destabilize this new Iraqi state
that the U.S. just propped up.
Even when the Kurds fight
on the side of the U.S.
and their interests,
U.S. support for their cause
still remains very limited.
They still look the other way
as Turkey bombs their towns
in Iraq hunting for the PKK.
This same pattern has
continued in recent years
in the country of Syria,
a country that descended
into civil war around 2011.
This chaos looked like an opportunity
for the Kurds in Syria, a
chance to establish real control
over what they see as a part of Kurdistan.
The PKK in Turkey helps
create a new Kurdish militia
called the People's
Protection Unit or YPG.
They seize large swaths
of land in the north
and they declare self-governance.
Around this same time,
the terrorist group ISIS
is taking huge swaths of territory
in the north and east of the country,
creating their so-called caliphate.
And here comes the U.S. once again
asking the Kurds for help,
hoping that they will fight against ISIS
on the ground for them.
But because this group
is allied with the PKK,
which they consider a terrorist group,
the U.S. asks this militia
to rebrand themselves
to the Syrian Democratic Forces,
which obscures their
connection to the PKK.
The U.S. then trains, funds,
and arms them to fight ISIS.
The Kurds are, once
again, the U.S.'s weapon.
This plan works, and with
help from U.S. airstrikes,
this Kurdish militia kicks
ISIS out of more and more land.
But Turkey hates this.
All they see is a potential Kurdish state
right on their southern border,
a safe haven for the PKK
that will allow more attacks
against the Turkish military.
But Turkey can't attack
this branch of the Kurds
while they're being supported
by the United States.
Lucky for them, there's a new
president in the White House
and he's promised to pull the
U.S. out of the war in Syria.
And in 2019, to the dismay of the Kurds,
he makes good on this promise.
With the U.S. out of
the way, Turkey invades,
launching airstrikes and artillery
against the Kurds in this border region,
saying that their plan is to create
a 32-kilometer-deep safe zone
right here along the border,
and that no Kurdish forces
are allowed to be here.
The plan was to then
resettle Syrian refugees
currently living in Turkey.
It's a brutal campaign
that looks a lot like what Syria was doing
to the Kurds in the '70s.
(missile whooshes)
The U.S. completely abandons the Kurds,
even after using them to
fight their enemy ISIS.
Turkey, a NATO and U.S.
ally, continues to bomb them
using weapons from the United States.
They spend the next four
years sending drone strikes
and airstrikes into Syria and Iraq,
anywhere they think
the PKK has a presence.
(subdued music)
This map shows all of their
attacks during this time.
You can see that it's not just
against the Kurds in Turkey,
but across this whole region.
Today, the Kurdish groups in this region
vary more widely than ever,
each with different values
and visions for the future,
forged from each of their
unique struggles and traumas.
Kurdish groups still fight
the government in Iran
with the goal of creating their own state.
The Kurds in Iraq did gain
some autonomy from the U.S.
in the new Iraqi constitution,
but it doesn't seem like
this autonomy will last.
As recently, the Iraqi Army
is fighting with the Kurds
to maintain control over the
oil resources in this area
to keep the Kurds economically dependent
on the central government so
that they never break away.
Once again, the U.S. is
not supporting the Kurds
in this fight.
Turkey continues its
offensive against the PKK
and other Kurdish groups in the region,
and they continue to crack
down on the Kurds politically,
arresting Kurdish
politicians and activists,
censoring journalists to
intimidate the Kurdish people
from participating in the election.
The Kurds in Syria face a
new and uncertain future.
They do have some autonomy
up here in the north,
but are surrounded by enemies,
no longer counting on
any support from the U.S.
The story of the Kurds
is the story of a people
who are willing to fight like few others,
all in the name of their
culture and identity.
That willingness to fight
has presented a threat
to regional governments, bent
on control of their people
and the resources within their borders.
That willingness to fight
has also been hijacked
by outside powers, turning
the Kurds into a pawn
to fulfill geopolitical objectives,
each time showing how
willing these powers are
to use the Kurds and
then abandon their cause.
(tense music)
(leader speaking in foreign language)
- [Interviewer] Do the
Palestinians have a right
to a separate state?
- [Netanyahu] No, I don't
think they do. But...
- In 2007, the head of
military intelligence
for the Israeli army had a meeting
with the U.S. Ambassador in Tel Aviv.
We're looking at the classified cable
that summarizes what was
talked about in this meeting.
The topic of discussion was Iran, Syria,
the Gaza Strip, and Hamas.
(loudspeaker blares)
Hamas had just won the
Palestinian elections,
which kicked off a fight with
the other Palestinian group,
which ended in Hamas taking
over Gaza completely.
They controlled it.
And if you're an Israeli
citizen or the U.S. government,
this is a terrible set of events.
Hamas is a violent extremist group
known to commit heinous violence
against civilians in Israel,
and they were now in power.
They controlled the Gaza Strip
an hour away from Tel Aviv.
But look at this leaked document.
In this leaked cable,
you see that the Israeli official says
that Israel would be happy
if Hamas took over Gaza
because it would mean that
Israel could now treat Gaza
like a hostile country.
- [Reporter] Three days post cease fire,
and there's unrelenting bombing in Gaza.
- This document is a view into a strategy
that right-wing factions
within the Israeli government
have used for decades in an effort
to win one of the most divisive conflicts
in the world today,
in which two groups are fighting
over one piece of holy land
and one side is winning by
using a very specific tactic,
one that the world says
is illegal and immoral,
and one that worked for a short time,
but that recently has been shown
to be a recipe for even worse violence
and conflict and suffering.
(serious music)
In this video, I wanna lay out
what this strategy looks like
and show you how it failed.
I know this is a topic that
is full of deep emotions
that has real stakes in people's lives.
Please know that I am
earnest in my efforts
to tell this story with
clarity and with accuracy.
And also please note that
this is not a full account
of the conflict between
Israel and its neighbors,
but I do hope that it sheds
light on a view of the conflict
that sometimes gets lost
in all of the yelling.
(Netanyahu speaking in foreign language)
(crowd cheering)
(subdued music)
For 2,000 years, Jewish
people around the world
have been persecuted and segregated
and ostracized from society.
That is a fact.
By the time the 1800s came around,
it became clear that
wherever the Jews went,
persecution would follow.
This is when a movement
emerged calling for Jews
to come together and to create
a country for themselves
where they could govern themselves
and be free from all
of this racist hatred.
The creation of a Jewish country
would have at the top of its priority list
the security of the Jewish people.
But the big question was where?
Several places floated
around in proposals,
Argentina, even modern-day Kenya,
which back then was Uganda.
But most people in this
movement wanted the Jews
to return to their historic homeland,
a place called Palestine.
(gentle music)
Where Jews built their temple
and their culture 3,000 years ago,
but then were exiled,
and now there was this call to return
so that Jews could feel safe
after 18 centuries of Jewish suffering.
So as the 1900s came around,
tens of thousands of
Jews, mostly from Europe,
flocked to Palestine,
which eventually came under
control of the British.
The British were getting
ready to leave this region
and were struggling to
contain the growing conflict
between native Arabs and
all these Jewish immigrants.
Then in the 1940s came a horrific genocide
against the Jewish people in Europe,
led out by Hitler and his Nazi regime.
This created a wave of
international support
for this idea of giving the Jewish people
a homeland where they could be safe.
Before they left, the British asked the UN
to determine what would
replace them in Palestine,
and the UN decided that Palestine
would become two new countries,
one for the Jews and one
for the Palestinian Arabs
that had already been
living in this region.
- [Reporter] The Jewish
state colored light,
the Arab state dark.
Jaffa to go to the Arabs,
Jerusalem internationalized.
- But as happens when outsiders
draw lines on old land,
there was a problem here.
Within these borders
that were meant for
the new Jewish country,
hundreds of thousands of
Palestinian Arabs were living
who would soon have to leave their homes
to move to their side of the line.
(gentle distressing music)
Okay, wait. I'm gonna pause there.
Because as I said this
is not a full history
of the Arab-Israeli conflict.
We actually just made a video
on our new channel Search Party,
which focuses on what happens next,
the conflict between Israel
and its Arab neighbors.
You can go watch that.
Link's in the description.
It'll give you some useful context.
For now just know that this
led to a horrific conflict.
Jewish militias forced over 700,000 Arabs
out of their homes turning
them into refugees.
The proposed borders shifted around,
turned into ceasefire lines,
and after all was said and done,
the Jewish people did indeed
get their own country,
the state of Israel.
(lofty music)
And the two important points
here are that number one,
the very foundation of the Israeli country
is for security of the Jewish people
after nearly 2,000 years of persecution.
And number two, the location
they chose to set it up
was becoming, as a
result of this conflict,
not much safer than Europe.
That's a tension that
follows this whole story.
(inquisitive music)
Okay, so now let's fast forward to 1967.
Israel has its country
and they fight a short war
with their Arab neighbors,
and they win that war and they
take over all of this land.
It's a huge victory for them.
I'm gonna take away the
Sinai Peninsula from here
because they did give that back to Egypt
as part of a peace deal a few years later.
Israel now controls
important pieces of land
that enlarge their Jewish country.
Many saw this victory as a sign from God
that they were actually
entitled to be here.
But once again, Palestinians,
nearly a million of whom had
been kicked out of their homes,
were living here in the West
Bank and the Gaza Strip,
which Israel now controlled,
but they weren't really
sure what to do with it.
And it's this territory
that would become the stage
for the strategy that is
the topic of this video,
where over time this
land would be sliced up
with roads and checkpoints,
walls and other military infrastructure
that would control the movement
and lives of the Palestinians.
Soon, even Israeli citizens
would start to move out here
in large numbers building full-on towns
and further dividing up this territory.
Moving citizens into
occupied territory like this
is something that the world
has deemed illegal and immoral.
So this occupation starts in 1967
and it goes on for decades,
until eventually the
Palestinians living here
can't handle it anymore and
they start fighting back.
(intense music)
This is known as the first
uprising or Intifada.
It started with boycotts,
but escalated into mass protests
where Palestinians of all
ages would throw stones
and sometimes Molotov cocktails
at much better-equipped Israeli soldiers.
It was Palestinian rage exploding
against Israeli occupation,
and it went on for years.
The Israeli government would
respond by cracking down,
killing many Palestinians.
Another important thing that
happens around the same time
down in the occupied Gaza Strip
is that a new movement forms
promising to fight back
against this occupation
calling for the destruction of Israel.
The group is called Hamas.
The first Intifada showed
that this wasn't gonna work.
Chopping up Palestinian
land, oppressing them,
keeping them in this occupation,
was only going to produce more violence.
It wasn't gonna fulfill Israel's promise
to provide security and
safety for the Jewish people.
They had to switch course.
- The security of the Israeli
people will be reconciled
with the hopes of the Palestinian people
and there will be more
security and more hope for all.
- [Johnny] So in the 1990s,
they start getting
serious about peace talks
with the Palestinians,
and they come to this agreement
called the Oslo Accords,
(stirring music)
which for the first time establishes
a Palestinian government authority
and giving it power to
govern pockets of land
in the West Bank.
It also gave the
Palestinians some authority
over almost all of the Gaza Strip,
though there were still
settlements in all of these places.
This was a big deal for this conflict.
Like, both sides were
talking to each other
and coming to agreements
that was giving, like,
authority to the Palestinians.
But another theme of the story
is that hardliners can use
violence to derail peace.
And that's exactly what happened here.
(protesters chant)
(brooding music)
Right-wing Israelis start holding rallies,
calling their Prime Minister
a traitor and a Nazi
for giving land to the Palestinians.
Some of these rallies are led
by a now familiar character,
Benjamin Netanyahu.
- The people of Israel want a real peace
and real peace means peace with security.
Peace they can trust with
a partner they can trust,
and they don't feel they have it here.
We want a real peace, not a fake one.
- [Johnny] But the peace talks continue.
- With all our neighbors,
a comprehensive peace.
- And shortly after signing
the second part of this deal
to give Palestinians some land,
the Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin
is assassinated by a far-right Israeli.
Hamas conducts bus bombings.
And the next year, Benjamin Netanyahu
is elected as the prime
minister of Israel.
And Netanyahu is a key
figure in this story
because his worldview
embodies a way of thinking
that has taken root in
Israel in recent years.
The idea that the only
way to give true security
to the Jewish people is by
doing whatever is necessary
to stop the Palestinians
from having a state
anywhere in these borders.
(gentle music)
- Look, I'm 28 years old.
I've had to defend my country
in two wars and in many battles.
Nobody wants peace more than Israel.
But the stumbling block
to the road for peace
is this demand for a PLO state,
which will mean more war,
which will mean more
violence in the Middle East.
And I think, I sincerely believe,
if this demand is abandoned,
we can have real and genuine peace.
- So that was Netanyahu.
He was a 28-year-old.
But when he becomes the prime minister
a couple decades later,
he spends his term
sabotaging the peace accords
that his predecessor had
worked so hard to create,
claiming that the
occupation of all this land
and its people wasn't actually conquest,
but rather the key for
security of the Jewish people.
They had to do this.
Security was the one and only
justification for all of this.
So under his watch settlers continue
to move into the West Bank.
We found this leaked video
of Benjamin Netanyahu
talking to some settlers in the West Bank.
(all speaking in foreign language)
- The cameraman does turn
off the camera for a moment,
but then turns it back on moments later.
(Netanyahu speaking foreign language)
- He is admitting to
sabotaging the peace accords
that the Israeli government had signed
with the Palestinians,
that because he disagreed with them,
he wanted to sabotage them
because he was so against
a Palestinian state
or any form of Palestinian
autonomy in this land.
And then he goes on to explain
what his real thinking
is on the situation.
(Netanyahu speaking foreign language)
- Netanyahu is a fantastic
politician and statesman,
and he's able to sort of cover
up a lot of these policies
in the name of security.
But here we see what he really thinks
as he's talking to these settlers
thinking he's not being recorded.
So unsurprisingly the
appetite for peace breaks down
on both sides.
Palestinians come to the conclusion
that the Israelis aren't really serious
about giving them any kind of autonomy
in the West Bank or Gaza,
that their situation will never change.
And once again, they rise
up in a second Intifada.
This one, much more violent,
much more coordinated.
(intense music)
Hamas becomes a major
player in the violence
with suicide bombings and attacks.
Israel responds with great
force and during the fighting,
1,000 Israelis and 3,000
Palestinians are killed.
At this point the Netanyahu
way of seeing the world
is starting to look a lot better.
Peace talks didn't work.
All they did was produce more violence.
And so maybe the only
way to ensure security
is to go back to full-blown occupation
of controlling every
move of the Palestinians
in the West Bank and the Gaza Strip.
So at this point the occupation
gets more and more suffocating,
more walls, more barriers,
more checkpoints, more settlements.
Then in 2005, Israel
withdraws from the Gaza Strip,
letting the Palestinian Authority
have total control there.
They turn their attention entirely
to their historic homeland
of Judea and Samaria,
which is the West Bank.
The next year, an election is held
in the Palestinian Authorities
and the winner surprised the world
and would create a new
chapter for this conflict.
The winner of these elections was Hamas.
- [Reporter] This is a
very, very bad result
for the Palestinians and for Israel.
- The incumbent Palestinian party
that had lost the election
tried to forcibly hold on to power,
and soon the two Palestinian parties
were fighting with each other.
And it results in this split
between the two Palestinian governments.
It turns into violence.
And when the dust settles,
there's suddenly a bitter divide
between these two Palestinian groups,
Hamas completely taking
over the Gaza Strip.
(subdued music)
And this gets us back
to our leaked document
that we started this video with
where an Israeli official is saying
that they would actually be happy
if Hamas took over the Gaza Strip
because now they can treat
Gaza like a hostile country.
(harrowing music)
(explosions boom)
Now that they're not occupying it,
they're not responsible
for the 2 million civilians
who are living there.
They can impose a blockade
to control anything coming
in and out of the Gaza Strip,
people, food, medicine,
money, building supplies.
But there was another
reason why Israel was happy
that Hamas now controlled the Gaza Strip.
The Palestinian government
was now deeply divided,
Hamas ruling Gaza and
the West Bank being run
by a more moderate, secular
Palestinian faction.
And crucially neither considered
the other to be legitimate,
which weakened their ability to negotiate
for any kind of state,
for any kind of country,
especially when Hamas still refused
to recognize Israel's right to even exist.
This division played right into the hands
of the Israeli right.
And this gets us back
to Benjamin Netanyahu,
that enemy of the earlier peace talks.
(brooding music)
He gets elected once again in 2009,
declaring himself Mr. Security
and promising to provide
safety to Israeli citizens
who are still shaken
from the second Intifada
and are now worried
that Hamas now controls
the entirety of the Gaza Strip.
Netanyahu's playbook
was already made clear.
He had said it point blank.
It's what he had been doing for years.
Sabotaging peace talks that
would give Palestinians
any kind of authority over this land,
and continuing to build settlements,
while continuing in his
words in that leaked tape
to hit the Palestinians hard
to make it unbearable for them.
A complete assault on the
Palestinian government.
Dividing and slowly conquering
the Palestinian people,
making life hard and desperate for them,
controlling their lives,
watching their every move.
And this is where we get to
this paradoxical alignment,
almost alliance between
Benjamin Netanyahu and Hamas,
the enemy of Israel.
(grim music)
As long as Hamas held
control over the Gaza Strip,
the Palestinian cause would
remain weak and divided.
Netanyahu would feel justified in imposing
this crippling blockade of the Gaza Strip,
which in turn gave Hamas legitimacy
among the people of the Gaza Strip,
showing that their armed struggle
against Israeli oppression was justified,
provoking them to launch
rockets into Israel
to show that they were
actually doing something
unlike the Palestinian
Authority in the West Bank,
which in turn bolstered
Netanyahu's narrative
that the Palestinians
actually don't want peace,
they want violence and
the destruction of Israel.
And the only way for security
is more occupation, more oppression.
So instead of try to take Hamas out,
Netanyahu overtly supported them
by approving huge transfers
of untraceable cash
literally delivered in
suitcases into the Gaza Strip,
cash that would inevitably
end up in the hands of Hamas
to be used against Israel.
He legitimized Hamas by
negotiating with them,
releasing a thousand Palestinian prisoners
in exchange for one Israeli.
- The Israeli soldier held
captive by Palestinian militants
for five years is expected
to be freed within days.
- The more Netanyahu could
keep Hamas in power in Gaza,
but keep them contained,
the more he could ensure that
Palestinians remain divided.
He could keep peace talks
from ever happening,
which in turn gave him time to continue
to pursue his expansionist
project in the West Bank.
And indeed, since 2009,
when Netanyahu became the Prime Minister,
the number of settlements in
the West Bank has only gone up.
(subdued music)
And if you look at this map,
you can see how these settlements
just weave through and carve up this land,
making it impossible to even fathom
what a Palestinian state could look like,
which is precisely the
point of the strategy.
I actually reported out here,
visiting the settlements
back when I was at Vox.
I did a series talking to the settlers,
trying to understand
why they live out there,
what it's like to live
in these settlements
that are strangely peaceful and banal
and just mundane, people
living their lives,
because they're protected by the army.
If you want a deeper dive on settlements,
you can go watch that series.
But if you're Netanyahu
over the last 16 years,
you think your plan is working.
Like, you see all these
settlements going up,
the international community
can't do anything about it.
They keep supporting you.
Every once in a while there's
some flare up in the West Bank
where Palestinians get into a
fight with Israeli soldiers,
but it gets contained.
Every few years Hamas fires some rockets,
which then gives Israel the
excuse to go, as they put it,
"cut the grass" by
conducting a short, swift,
violent military campaign
to keep Hamas at bay.
And every day that goes by,
the notion of a Palestinian state
becomes less and less feasible.
(subdued music)
This is one reason why a
far right Israeli lawmaker
called Hamas "an asset."
(pundit speaking in foreign language)
So divide and conquer has
been the name of the game
in Israel for a long time,
but especially in the last
16 years under Netanyahu.
And again, to the people in
charge, they think it's working.
Maybe this violent status
quo, this equilibrium can hold
and the far right can get
exactly what they want.
Security for the Jewish people
and expansion into all of this land.
And maybe the occupation will
break the Palestinian spirit
and they would give up on
their dream of having a state.
But that's not what happened.
On October 7th, 2023,
we saw how wrongheaded this
theory of security was.
- In an unprecedented surprise attack,
the militant Hamas rulers of Gaza
sent dozens of fighters into
Israel by land, sea, and air.
- This deadly attack launched by Hamas
showed us that while Netanyahu's strategy
of divide and conquer might be good
for taking over more land,
what it's not good for is making good
on the original promise of Israel,
which is ensuring the
security of the Jewish people.
In fact, his strategy has
produced exactly the opposite.
(crowd chanting in foreign language)
Now, the responsibility for
what happened on October 7th
lies with the people who
committed those acts of terror,
Hamas fighters and their leaders.
There is no excuse or
justification for their actions.
But the point I'm trying
to make with this video
is that there's also others
that need to stand accountable here.
Those who used Hamas as a pawn
to continue this
divide-and-conquer policy,
who are now engaged in a campaign
of mass bloodshed on civilians,
they deserve to stand accountable as well,
to the Israeli people
and to the countries that support Israel.
I believe in the need
for a Jewish state. I do.
I think that's a very reasonable proposal
that Jewish people should feel
safe somewhere in this world.
And yet what we're looking at isn't it.
The Israeli project,
the way that it's been
wielded in its current form,
produces the exact opposite
of security for the Jewish people.
(serious music)
Look at this map.
This map shows the thousands of attacks
that have occurred right
here on this border
just over the past year in
this fight between Israel
and one of their biggest
regional enemies, Hezbollah.
(soldiers chanting in foreign language)
Hezbollah is one of the biggest
armed groups in the world
that isn't a nation's military.
They have tens of thousands
of trained soldiers
and hundreds of thousands
of missiles and rockets
capable of reaching
targets all across Israel.
This threat led Israel
to conduct a massive set of
attacks against Hezbollah.
- [Reporter] This large explosion was seen
near Beirut International Airport.
- [Johnny] In which they killed
almost all of the group's top leaders
weakening Hezbollah immensely,
followed by a full-on
invasion by Israeli troops
to denigrate this group even further.
This has been a massive escalation
that is now spilling over
into this entire region.
And to understand how we got here,
you really have to understand
where Hezbollah came from
and what this group's fierce
40-year struggle tells us
about how the modern
Middle East came together
and how it's now coming apart.
(grim music)
The story of Hezbollah really starts
when the vast Ottoman Empire broke apart
in the early 1900s.
Europeans came in and
sliced all of this up,
France taking all of this territory,
but then they drew a line here
to carve out this little
mountainous region,
one that was populated mostly
by Maronite Christians,
but the border didn't
include just Christians.
The French made sure to
include this area to the east
and this area to the south.
Areas that contained large
populations of Shia Muslims
who were now forced into this new country
where they were made a
minority to the Christians
along with a few other religious groups.
We're gonna focus a lot down
here on this Shia heartland
that would eventually become one of
the most important regions
in the whole Middle East.
(suspenseful music)
(subdued music)
In 1943, Lebanon gains its
independence from France.
It creates a constitution
meant to balance the power
between all of these religious groups,
but that balance wouldn't last.
Mostly thanks to what
started happening down here
where another set of
borders were being carved
into the Middle East.
The British had controlled
this, but in 1948, they left
and the UN helped draw these new lines,
creating a new Israel
and Palestinian state.
Decades of war forced out
millions of Palestinians,
many of whom ended up here in Lebanon.
These Palestinians are
mostly Sunni Muslim,
so this upsets the carefully
laid power balance in Lebanon
and further marginalizes the Shia Muslims
who were fighting for
their place in the country.
Then in 1971, an armed militia
made up of Palestinians
called the Palestinian
Liberation Organization
moves to Lebanon,
and they turn this whole region,
which, again, was made up of mostly Shias,
into their own little mini state.
You start to see that Lebanon
is descending into division
between the different militias
and powers controlling
parts of the country.
And in the mid '70s,
it all breaks down into
a full-fledged civil war
between a dizzying number
of religious factions.
It's a war that will pull
in much of the Middle East,
(grim music)
and it's a war whose most
important region is down here
in this border zone
between Israel and Lebanon.
The place that will soon
give rise to Hezbollah.
Now, let's talk about Syria.
They're here right next door,
and they're watching this civil war
and they decide to invade,
to prop up the Maronite
Christian ruling class
who've become Syria allies.
They want to do this to
prevent the Civil War
from spilling over into their territory.
At this point, Syria
also considers annexing
the entire country of Lebanon,
making it a part of Syria.
But eventually, the
relationship between Syria
and Maronite Christians breaks down,
and Syria continues to occupy
this part of the country.
Meanwhile, to the south,
Israel fears that Syria
is growing too powerful.
It also wants to wipe out the PLO,
who is attacking them across
the border from Lebanon.
So in 1978, Israel enters the
fray invading from the south
and driving deep into the country.
Israel succeeds in temporarily
suppressing the PLO,
but in the process,
it displaces hundreds
of thousands of locals,
most of them Shia Muslims.
It eventually withdraws
after a UN resolution.
But then, in 1982, after more PLO attacks,
Israel invades again,
this time pushing all the way to Beirut,
fighting both the PLO and Syria.
And this is where the conflict
takes on a new dimension.
(high-strung music)
It's 1979 and over in Iran,
the people have risen up
against the U.S.-backed dictator
in this Islamic revolution
led by a Shia Muslim cleric
who wants to spread this
revolution throughout the region.
He's looking for allies,
and in 1982, they find their perfect match
here in southern Lebanon.
It's a militia that rose
to defend against outsiders
trampling their heartland.
It's called the Hezbollah,
which means party of God.
Iran picked this group in particular
because it shares its
goals of Islamic Revolution
and a deep distrust
and disdain for Israel.
Iran starts providing Hezbollah
with money, weapons, soldiers,
training, and leadership.
And in return, Hezbollah proclaims loyalty
to the Iranian Revolution
and its supreme leader.
What started as Lebanon's civil war
is now a regional war that is heating up.
So the United States enters
leading an international
peacekeeping mission
to try to calm these tensions.
But of course, Hezbollah
and Iran hate this.
They now have two prime
targets in their backyard,
Israel, and these Western
powers led by the U.S..
So in 1983, they launched a
series of terrorist attacks,
a truck bomb detonated in front of
a U.S. and French barracks in Beirut
that kills over 300 people.
Most of the world blames
not only Hezbollah,
but also its backer, Iran.
The fighting continues until 1989
when the many groups
fighting this civil war
come to a peace agreement,
one that bans all militias
and requires them to give their weapons
back to the government.
But there's a big catch here.
Israel still occupies
what they call this security buffer zone
in southern Lebanon.
So the peace agreement makes an exception
specifically for efforts that
resist the Israeli occupation,
a.k.a, they allow Hezbollah
to continue to exist,
turning them into something more
than just one of these militias
fighting for their group.
It gives them a kind of official status
to continue acting as a
defender of southern Lebanon,
the country's bulwark against Israel.
They also develop into
more of a political party
that gains seats in Lebanon's legislature,
kind of serving as a parallel government
providing social services in
the areas that it controls.
(subdued music)
So let's look at Hezbollah in this moment,
because they find themselves
in the middle of shifting
power games in the Middle East,
balancing their mandate to
defend their Shia heartland,
which was their founding motivation,
but also trying to gain
further influence in the region
while also appeasing the demands
of their major supporter, Iran.
In 2005, Lebanon's prime
minister is assassinated,
and most Lebanese blame Hezbollah,
along with its other
foreign supporter, Syria,
Lebanese people rise up in mass protest,
and Syria eventually withdraws its forces
that have occupied Lebanon for 28 years.
Hezbollah is disgraced.
Its legitimacy is supposed
to come from resisting foreign meddling,
and it's becoming clear
that they have become a pawn
in the geopolitical game of
regional powers, Syria and Iran.
But the group is able to
turn Syria's withdrawal
into their advantage.
The Syrian occupation had
kept Lebanon somewhat stable,
so as soon as they left, it
creates this power vacuum
and allows Hezbollah
to take more territory,
ramping up attacks across
the border against Israel
and leading to another
brief war with the IDF.
Hezbollah continues to be
a useful proxy for Iran,
and Iran continues to
fund them and arm them.
And by 2011, Iran and Syria pull Hezbollah
into another unpopular
conflict, Syria's civil war.
But this hurts Hezbollah's reputation
because now they're fighting
on behalf of Syria's
brutal Iran-backed regime.
These once-liberators
have turned into foot
soldiers of oppression
doing the bidding of outsiders.
But its last source of legitimacy
continues to be its resistance to Israel,
something that Lebanon's own
government is too weak to do.
This remains their source
of legitimacy today.
So on October 7th, 2023,
when Hamas and Israel descended
into this most recent war,
Hezbollah jumped in,
launching more attacks against
Lebanon's southern border.
This is meant to support
Hamas in the Gaza Strip
and to threaten Israel
with a war on two fronts.
At first, it seemed to be working.
Tens of thousands of
Israelis have had to evacuate
the towns and villages in northern Israel.
So Israel started firing
back across the border,
forcing 90,000 people in southern
Lebanon from their homes.
This, in addition to Israeli strikes
on Iranian proxies and military officials,
led Iran to fire its first
ever direct strike on Israel,
trying to deter it from going any further,
but it didn't work.
In September of 2024, Israel escalated,
surprising Hezbollah
with a series of attacks
that killed a large part of
the group's top leadership,
including their decades-long leader.
A few days later, Israel sent
troops across this border
with the goal of further
weakening Hezbollah,
trying to make the situation safe
for Israelis to return home
to the north of the country.
And now with Hezbollah in shambles,
its sponsor, Iran, felt compelled to act.
(missiles exploding)
- Oh, Jesus.
- [Danna] What we are all
seeing with our own eyes
is a major attack from Iran.
- [Reporter] It's a major attack, Danna,
and it's an escalation.
It's an escalation...
- [Johnny] So even if Hezbollah
eventually begins to rebuild itself,
it's unclear what role they will play
in Iran's proxy network.
But what is clear is that the clash
between these two Middle East powers
remains the central force
animating this region
towards more and more violence.
And these recent events
show us clearer than ever
that Hezbollah was just one foot soldier
in this growing conflict
between these two powers.
Checking in one last time to remind you
that this video is made
possible by Ground News,
the sponsor of this compilation.
Ground News is the service that I use
to look deeper into the
headlines that I'm consuming,
very, very deeply aligned
with their mission
to help reveal the narratives
behind all of the many headlines
that are covering the world's news.
If you wanna get 40%
off their Vantage Plan,
which is the one I use,
you can go to ground.news/johnnyharris
to get in on that discount
and support this very useful service.
Okay, onto the next video.
(subdued music)
Along the banks of the most
important waterway on earth
sits the country of Yemen,
a place that was two countries for decades
until the year 1990,
when it was unified into one.
A fragile patchwork of groups
all with different tribal
backgrounds, religious beliefs,
and political aspirations.
The story I want to
tell starts in the '90s,
when one group forms up in the
northern mountains of Yemen.
It's started by a group
of religious Yemenis
who call themselves the Believing Youth,
who were members of a Shiite
Muslim sect called the Zaidi.
Zaidi Muslims used to be the majority
when the country was split in two.
But in the new unified Yemen,
they became a minority
and felt neglected and
discriminated against.
At first, the group focuses
on rebuilding the Zaidi
religious identity,
hosting summer camps for young men
and offering religious education.
But in the late 1990s,
the group starts to
change in important ways.
A member of Yemen's
parliament resigns in protest
and joins the Believing Youth.
He felt that the government
of Yemen was corrupt
and far too influenced
by Yemen's neighbor to
the north, Saudi Arabia.
Al Houthi blamed outside influence
for many of the country's problems.
So as he leaves the government,
Al Houthi uses his wealth
and family connections
in the Zaidi community
to become the leader
of the Believing Youth.
He wants an Islamic revolution,
modeled after the one in Iran.
One that kicks out any foreign influence
and restores Islamic values.
- [Reporter] Outrage with
the speed of the human shout.
- [Johnny] With Al Houthi's influence,
this group of young men in the
mountainous region of Yemen
starts to change.
They begin protesting Yemen's
president, Ali Abdullah Saleh.
Soon they start taking up
weapons, taking over territory,
and eventually setting up
their own security checkpoints
in their region.
The Believing Youth are starting
to look a lot less like a summer camp
and a lot more like a
militia, like a rebellion.
President Saleh,
who had previously supported
the Believing Youth,
is starting to get worried.
And then in 2001,
the entire Middle East
would change forever.
(dark music)
After 9/11, the U.S.
launches a war on terror.
(reflective music)
They asked President Saleh for help,
and he cooperates, taking military aid
and allowing American special forces
to operate inside Yemen,
where the terrorist group
Al-Qaeda has a presence.
18 months later,
the U.S. presence in the
region would balloon even more
when the American military
invades and occupies Iraq.
For Al Houthi and his group of young men,
this crosses a red line and
deeply radicalizes the movement.
Al Houthi criticizes
the president publicly
for pandering to what he
sees as American imperialism
in Muslim lands.
And many in Yemen agree,
joining the movement and
bolstering their numbers.
Al Houthi adopts the violent slogan
that sits on the flag of
his movement to this day:
God is great. Death to America.
Death to Israel. Curse on the Jews.
Victory to Islam.
President Saleh feels
threatened by the growth
of this increasingly radical movement
that is taking control of
territory in the north.
He issues an arrest warrant
and a bounty for Al Houthi
and brutally cracks
down on their protests.
In response, the Believing
Youth launch an armed rebellion
in the north of Yemen,
leading to counterattacks
by the Yemeni military.
Shortly after the fighting begins,
Al Houthi is killed in
a cave in the north.
The rebels he leaves behind
fight on with new conviction,
and the world would know them
by the name of their martyr,
a symbol of imperial resistance
that would soon be
firing rockets at Israel
and hijacking cargo ships in the Red Sea.
(subdued music)
By 2004, the Houthis have morphed
into a full-blown rebellion,
fighting against Yemen's government
from their northern strongholds.
They know this land well
and they have local support,
allowing them to fight
a guerrilla campaign
against the government forces,
blending in with civilians,
hiding in mountains and caves,
and allowing them to resist
the much better-equipped Yemeni army.
As the conflict turns more violent,
more tribes in the region would feel
that the military is being overly brutal,
leading them to join the Houthis.
And it's at this time that the
conflict goes international.
The Houthis say that Saudi Arabia
is letting the government of Yemen
position troops right across this border.
So they invade into Saudi Arabia,
killing Saudi soldiers
and taking hostages.
This pulls Saudi Arabia into the conflict,
as they respond with airstrikes and troops
and push the Houthis
out of their territory,
punishing them for this invasion.
Now, over here, Iran is watching this war,
and they see an opportunity.
The Houthis are now fighting directly
against their biggest rival, Saudi Arabia.
So they start secretly sending
weapons to the Houthis.
At least that's what Saudi Arabia claims,
saying that they
intercepted an Iranian ship
filled with weapons and military trainers
on their way to the Houthis.
It looks like Iran is directly
supporting the Houthis now.
Though how much support they
provide behind the scenes
will always be intentionally unclear.
As the conflict between the Houthis
and the government continues in the north,
Saudi Arabia has been fighting
their own war on terror
against a branch of Al-Qaeda
operating in Saudi Arabia.
Seeing that their days are numbered,
this branch of Al-Qaeda flees south
over the border into Yemen,
where they merge their forces
with the Yemen branch of Al-Qaeda.
They create Al-Qaeda in the
Arabian Peninsula, or AQAP,
one of the most dangerous
and well-funded versions
of the group to ever exist.
The group's goal is to
create a strict Islamic state
across the whole region,
while violently waging holy war
against foreigners in Muslim lands.
(reflective music)
This puts them at odds with
both the Yemeni government
and the Houthis.
The conflict is getting more complicated.
Around 2011, the region
starts to change in big ways.
In one country after another,
there's an outpouring of
public anger on the streets,
demanding change from their government,
removing old leaders.
This is called the Arab Spring.
It's upheaval that spirals the
region into hope and chaos.
(protesters chanting in foreign language)
- [Johnny] Iran and Saudi Arabia
see this as an opportunity
to strategically choose sides
in all of these countries,
in hopes that when the dust settles,
they will come out with
a stronger hand of allies
in the region.
And one of their main focuses is Yemen,
a country that is also rising up,
calling for President Saleh to step down.
The corrupt dictator of
Yemen is running out of time,
which is something the Houthis
have been fighting for for years.
But Saleh refuses to step down,
adding fuel to the uprising.
Saudi Arabia sees this situation
at their southern border
and decides to step in
with the help of the UN,
convincing Saleh to transfer
power to his vice president,
in exchange for immunity from prosecution.
On his way out, Saleh takes
the billions of dollars
that he corruptly amassed
during his time in office,
and he also retains the loyalty
of key parts of the military,
fighters that are only loyal to him.
But the people aren't satisfied
with this new Saudi-backed president.
The government remains
weak and unorganized.
Meanwhile, the Houthis
are taking advantage
of this infighting and
only getting stronger,
taking more and more
territory from the government,
adding to their forces,
and receiving more support
from their backer, Iran,
who is supplying them with
more training, missiles,
drones, and other advanced weapons.
They use these weapons in the fall of 2014
to march into southern Yemen,
taking over large swaths of territory.
Now that the Houthis have momentum,
the former President Saleh joins them
in an alliance of convenience.
In fact, Saleh's forces are critical
in helping the Houthis take
the capital city of Sanaa.
Saleh is now working
with his former enemy,
against his own vice president,
the man he had to give power
to when he stepped down.
President Hadi and his
government flee south
as the Houthis take over,
but the Houthis are right behind them.
So Hadi has to flee to Saudi Arabia,
trying to govern Yemen from there.
But the Houthis just
keep gaining momentum.
By the middle of 2015,
they now control the
capital city completely,
where they create their own government
and take control of the
government's military weapons,
helping them expand even
further into the south.
Now that the Houthis are in power,
they run an oppressive regime
that silences free speech,
crushes dissent through
arrest and torture,
and recruits children as soldiers,
all while imposing strict religious laws
that undermine women's rights.
Meanwhile, Saudi Arabia
is getting nervous.
Their southern neighbor is now controlled
by a group that is funded
by their biggest enemy.
So they recruit the support of countries
around the region and invade Yemen,
with the goal of removing
the Houthis from power.
The war is led by Crown
Prince Mohammed bin Salman,
Saudi Arabia's up-and-coming
leader and defense minister.
He starts with a
widespread bombing campaign
and a naval blockade
that prevents shipping in
and out of the country,
with the goal of trying to cut off support
coming in from Iran.
The crown prince turns
to the United States
in need of more weapons for this war.
While the U.S. leaders are
reluctant to get involved
in another Middle East conflict,
they also want to maintain
a good relationship
with Saudi Arabia, who
is their major security
and energy partner in the region.
They also have an interest
in weakening Al-Qaeda's
growing presence in Yemen.
So in addition to supporting this war
with logistics and intelligence,
President Obama approves
billions of dollars of weapons:
planes, tanks, and even weapons
banned by most of the world
for how dangerous they are for civilians,
like cluster munitions.
(tense music)
This quickly turns Saudi Arabia
into the largest importer
of American weapons for
the next four years.
So it's 2015,
and Yemen is in a full-blown
war between the Houthis
and Saudi Arabia and their coalition.
This is when Al-Qaeda,
who's not on either side,
takes advantage of this chaos
and makes a land grab
in the middle of Yemen.
They take major cities and
clash with government forces.
Also taking advantage of the instability
is the terrorist group ISIS,
who come to Yemen and fight
the Houthis and Al-Qaeda,
at the same time.
Though their attacks are scattered,
and they don't control
significant territory.
The U.S. then gets more
involved by launching airstrikes
at Al-Qaeda and ISIS targets
to stop them from gaining
any more territory.
They tried to kill their leadership.
But the U.S. has to do this carefully
because they don't want
to engage the Houthis.
Their fight is with Al-Qaeda and ISIS.
In May of 2015, the Houthis attack a city
just across the border in Saudi Arabia,
killing two and taking hostages,
forcing an airport to shut down.
The crown prince doesn't take
being attacked on his own soil lightly,
especially by Iran's proxies.
So over the next 24 hours,
the Saudis launch 130 airstrikes in Yemen,
hitting homes, schools, and hospitals.
Thousands are forced to
flee from their home.
Hundreds are reported dead,
though we'll never know
the real death toll.
These strikes are almost
immediately called war crimes.
But the crown prince doesn't back down.
His coalition then sends in
ground troops from the south,
pushing back the Houthis and
taking back the city of Aden.
He's behaving as if he's fighting
his greatest enemy, Iran.
It's a vicious cycle that is
common in proxy wars like this,
and it lands the people of Yemen
in the worst humanitarian
crisis in the world.
The international community
tries to intervene
with diplomatic efforts
to stop the fighting.
But over the next six years,
those efforts would fail,
and Saudi Arabia would
continue its brutal campaign,
all using American weapons.
The Houthis continue to fight,
to show that they are legitimate,
that they are the government of Yemen.
They aren't just doing Iran's bidding.
(somber music)
The war continues to
destroy cities and land,
and the blockade continues
to keep trade out.
The Saudis continue to
bomb indiscriminately.
And with time, 2 million
Yemenis are displaced,
forced to leave their homes
to flee this violence.
- [Reporter] 150,000
civilians have had to-
- [Johnny] But this
doesn't stop the Houthis
from escalating their offensive.
They start attacking Saudi Arabia directly
with missiles and drones
in their capital city
and their civilian airports,
using weapons that most
believe are coming from Iran.
(tense music)
In December of 2017,
the Saudis and the UAE
convinced President Saleh
to break his alliance with the Houthis
and return to power as president of Yemen.
They hope that Saleh, the former dictator,
might be able to hold onto
power and rule more effectively.
Saleh takes the deal and
changes sides yet again,
breaking with the Houthis
and joining the Saudi-led coalition.
(reflective music)
Fighting breaks out between the Houthis
and Saleh's militias,
and Saleh is killed just two days later.
(reflective music)
Meanwhile, in the United
States, there's a new president.
President Trump orders
increased drone strikes
and raids against Al-Qaeda,
helping government forces
take back large amounts of territory.
Despite the war crimes committed
using American weapons,
Trump approves more weapons
sales to Saudi Arabia
to wage this war.
And then in 2018, the conflict
takes on a new dimension.
The UAE, who's a part of
the Saudi-led coalition,
is starting to lose faith
in the direction this war is going.
They don't like the current
government of Yemen,
and they're losing soldiers on the ground.
It's damaging their
reputation on the world stage.
So the UAE leaves the coalition.
But they still want to influence
who will ultimately control Yemen,
so they start backing a
new group in the south
called the Southern
Transitional Council, or STC.
This group isn't aligned with
the government or the Houthis.
They're calling for a separation
of the southern part of Yemen.
They want their own state.
They want their own country.
So the UAE starts to withdraw their troops
from the south of the country,
and the STC separatists
start taking control
of southern provinces.
The Saudi coalition is fracturing,
and yet another group is
jumping into the fighting,
showing just how up for
grabs Yemen has become.
By the fall of 2019, the war
has reached maximum complexity.
You've got the Saudi coalition
backing the former government of Yemen,
mostly relegated to the
east of the country.
The UAE is now backing
this separatist movement in the south,
who are fighting against the
former government of Yemen.
The Houthis, backed by Iran,
still maintain majority control
of the major cities in the north.
Al-Qaeda and its militia
allies are still fighting
to control small slices of the country.
And the U.S. continues
to conduct airstrikes
against Al-Qaeda and ISIS,
while supporting and selling more weapons
to the Saudi coalition.
Yemen is fracturing further,
and if there's any hope for peace,
power needs to be consolidated.
So Saudi Arabia and the UAE make amends,
and then, together, they
convince the government of Yemen
and the separatists in the
south to form a new coalition
to fight against the Houthis
together as a united front.
But it doesn't stop the Houthis,
who are getting really good at fighting
and are firing more
Iranian missiles and drones
into Saudi Arabia,
hitting state-owned oil refineries
and threatening to drive
up oil prices globally.
By January 2021, the
Houthis, a group started
to provide religious
summer camps to young men,
are now battle hardened,
and they control 70 to 80%
of the population of Yemen.
Later that year, the UN announces
that approximately 20
million of those people
are dependent on humanitarian
aid for their daily needs.
And at this point, the
war starts to settle in
to an uncomfortable stalemate.
(somber music)
In April 2022, the UN brokers a ceasefire,
and the fighting stops.
Behind the scenes,
Saudi Arabia and Iran have
been in diplomatic talks,
sponsored by China.
Regional tensions are cooling,
which means that their proxy
war in Yemen is also cooling.
Saudi Arabia has had
enough of the fighting.
President Hadi resigns
and hands power over
to a council meant to govern
Yemen and manage the war.
And both sides are tired of the fighting.
So when that ceasefire is set
to expire in October 2022,
the conflict mostly stays quiet,
even without a new agreement.
By 2023, Saudi Arabia and Iran
have officially restored
their diplomatic relations.
Saudi Arabia hoping that this means Iran
will stop supporting Houthis
to attack their southern border.
But the Saudis keep
their maritime blockade
around the country,
making life in Yemen
unlivable for millions.
But at this point,
the heaviest of the fighting
on all sides has stopped.
But then in the fall of 2023,
the Houthis were back in the news.
After the Palestinian group Hamas
launches a brutal attack into Israel,
the Israeli military
invades the Gaza Strip,
vowing to destroy Hamas
and free the hostages that they took.
The campaign leads to tens of thousands
of Palestinian civilian deaths,
and it provokes a response
from Iranian-backed groups
all throughout the region.
The Houthis are one of those groups.
They launch drones and cruise
missiles into southern Israel,
vowing that their attacks won't stop
until the invasion of Gaza stops.
And then they start firing
their missiles and drones
at cargo ships that are
traveling through the Red Sea,
where 25% of container traffic travels,
a major artery in our global economy.
In the days after these
missiles start flying,
traffic through this Red
Sea route declines by 73%.
In response, the U.S. and UK
shoot down Houthis missiles
and drop bombs on Houthis
military targets in Yemen,
pulling the U.S. and its allies deeper
into this enduring conflict.
(reflective music)
The reason I wanted to tell you the story
of this conflict in Yemen.
Because it represents
the vicious cycle present
in a lot of proxy wars,
where geopolitical rivals
use their neighbors as battlefields
instead of fighting each other directly.
They fund and add fuel to local conflicts,
escalating them to the entire country,
and often to the entire region,
leaving violence and power
vacuums in their wake,
which are then filled by bad actors
trying to take advantage
of the instability.
All of this changes borders,
destroys cities, and ruins lives.
It's the story of powerful countries
and their cynical scramble
for influence and power
in vulnerable places,
leaving behind them a wake of
tremendous human suffering.
(somber music)
(brooding music)
- [Reporter] Breaking news.
Because Yemen's Houthis rebels-
- [Reporter] They could
attack a commercial ship
and could bog the strait up
for weeks, if not months.
(protestors chanting in foreign language)
- [Johnny] There is a part of the world
that everyone is keeping
an eye on right now.
- The joint military
strikes were a response
to nearly two months of attacks
by the Iran-backed Houthis movement
on cargo ships in the Red Sea.
- [Johnny] It is becoming
more and more important
for the global rivalries and tensions
that are heating up on
our globe right now.
It is this choke point in the Red Sea.
(subdued music)
It's pretty small.
It's a few dozen kilometers wide,
but through this little choke point
flows a lot of important things.
The internet, millions of
barrels of oil per day,
30% of all container ships
that connect global markets.
And this choke point
is surrounded by unstable situations.
Countries that are in
civil wars, rebel militias,
proxy wars, unstable governments,
failed states, and pirates.
In recent decades,
pirates have hijacked
thousands of ships here
extracting hundreds of
millions of dollars in ransoms,
a topic we did a whole deep
dive on in another video.
And lately, as war has
raged in the Gaza Strip,
the fiercely anti-Western
Houthis rebels in Yemen
have been firing rockets at cargo ships
traveling through this water
leading the U.S. and UK to strike back.
- A ship attacked by Iran-backed
Houthis rebels last month
sank in the Red Sea.
- [Johnny] The region is vital,
yet volatile all at once.
And yet in the middle of all of this
is this one beacon of stability,
a little piece of land
that is easy to miss,
but that is more important
than you might think.
It is the country of Djibouti.
(tense music)
Djibouti is this small arid country
right on the choke point,
and it is home to the
militaries of the United States
of several European powers, of Japan,
Japan's only foreign
military base, by the way,
and right down the road
from the American base,
China's first military base
outside of its country.
(subdued music)
Qatar has peacekeepers here.
The United Arab Emirates
ran the biggest port.
Eritrea seized some of
its territory recently,
and Ethiopia, one of the
largest countries in Africa,
runs almost all of its
trade through Djibouti.
Ethiopia's landlocked, and this is their,
like, gateway to the world.
It's a lot. Djibouti is a lot.
There's a lot going on in Djibouti,
which is why today we are
talking about this place.
I want to explore why so
many powers want to be here,
why everyone is converging
on this little tiny patch of
land the size of New Jersey.
And I wanna ask if little Djibouti,
one of the poorest countries in the world,
can balance all these rival
powers against each other
without falling victim to them.
- [Austin] You know, 10
to 15% of global trade
moves through the Red Sea.
We will not hesitate to defend lives
and the free flow of commerce.
(subdued music)
- This little choke point
is called the Bab-el-Mandeb,
or Gate of Tears.
It used to be nothing but
a recipe for shipwrecks.
It was known mostly for strong winds,
unpredictable crosscurrents
and shallow reefs
that made navigating it dangerous.
And it wasn't very valuable
because if you go through it,
you just end up in the Red Sea,
which was a dead-end for most of history.
That is, until a French company
miraculously cut a canal
through this part of Egypt
and changed the world forever,
nearly halving the time
that it would take for
Europeans to get to Asia
where they were all racing each
other to conquer, colonize,
and bring back unfathomable
wealth to their countries.
The Suez Canal was a massive upgrade
to this hunt for resources.
Was this video kind of an excuse
for me to buy these really
old, beautiful books
about the Suez Canal?
Yes, it was.
For France, this engineering
miracle called the Suez Canal
was their chance to beat
out their big rival,
the British Empire, who was
clearly winning the race,
dominating the routes to
Asia before Suez opened.
The canal was supposed to change that.
So now you have a new front in this race,
a scramble for control over
this new route to Asia.
This windy little choke point
was no longer just the Gate of Tears.
It was an important bit of water,
one of the most important on earth,
at least for the empires,
they had to keep an eye on it.
So the British take this little island
right at the choke point.
They put a lighthouse on it.
They also take control
of a port just south of the choke point.
The Italians then show up
and purchase this bit of
coastline from local sultans
eventually taking over
this whole stretch of
coast called Eritrea.
And the French would start fixating
on this strip of sparsely populated coast
right on the banks of the choke point,
the land that would become Djibouti.
The sultans here told the French
that, yes, they could have a bit
of this newly strategic land
in exchange for protection.
The locals here knew what was going on.
The great empires were
all scrambling and racing,
and they were going to use
their prime real estate
to get what they wanted
to leverage the situation.
Smart and totally a theme
throughout this video.
So the French set up their colony,
they call it Cotes Francaises des Somalies
or French Somaliland.
This choke point would become a key base
for projecting power and refueling
on their way to carve up and plunder Asia.
(intense music)
France would hold on
to their little colonial
invention for a long time.
Even as the world would
decolonize after World War II,
France held on
to this strategic colony
along the choke point
until eventually the locals rose up.
There were protests,
they clashed with the local authorities,
and it led to an independence vote.
And in 1977, Djibouti
became a new country.
Djibouti was independent,
but they had a problem.
In the words of some "New York
Times" reporting from 1977,
the tiny new nation had no army,
less than one square mile of arable land,
and no resources
except for sand, salt, and 20,000 camels.
Yeah, not good.
So once again, they
made a deal with France.
Djibouti wouldn't be France's anymore,
but they would be allowed
to retain a military base in the country
in exchange for security and protection
as well as economic aid.
But this didn't change the fact
that Djibouti had very
little natural resources
or arable land.
Their economy fell into
a crippling depression.
Eventually there was a civil war
and it wasn't looking good for Djibouti.
Djibouti's salvation would eventually come
when they realized that
they should harken back
to the old days and start
exploiting the thing
that had made them valuable
all those years ago:
Their location.
- [Reporter] Let's go. Go, go, go, go!
Stop shooting, man. Go!
- A plane has crashed
into the World Trade-
- [Reporter] Can you tell
us how this happened?
- Not right now.
- Our very freedom came under attack
in a series of deliberate
and deadly terrorist acts.
- [Johnny] Three months after 9/11,
the United States was
about to come crashing
into the Middle East in a new way,
and they asked Djibouti if
they could set up a base there.
And Djibouti says yes.
- Suddenly after the global war on terror,
America realizes that it's
one of the key locations.
It matters to be there.
You had, you know, Al-Qaeda in Yemen,
you had Al-Qaeda and even Horn of Africa.
So they needed a base.
And Djibouti was one country
which was willing to offer it.
- It would become America's
only permanent military base
on the continent of Africa.
And it would be a key jumping-off point
for George Bush's war on terror.
And reminder that it's
now the 21st century.
Things have changed in the world.
And this little choke point
was becoming more valuable again,
but for different reasons
than the old days.
(ship horn blares)
Number one, the world had
become addicted to fossil fuels,
oil and gas, which was the
lifeblood of their economies.
And most of that oil and gas
was coming from over here,
from the land and waters
of the countries around this Persian Gulf
where it was then put on ships
and sent around the world,
a lot of it heading west
through this vital choke point
up the Red Sea into the
Suez Canal and onto Europe.
The world knew that their
energy was vulnerable
because Egypt in earlier decades
had weaponized the canal by
closing it, by blocking it.
One time for eight years,
inflicting immediate pain on the countries
that rely on this constant
flow of energy and goods.
By the way, semi side note,
this flow of energy
becomes even more important
when Europe almost entirely cuts ties
with Russian natural gas
after Russia invaded Ukraine in 2022.
So they have to get more
natural gas from this region.
Qatar was not sad about
that, let's put it that way.
Anyway, we're getting off topic.
Europe needs this route to stay stable.
They need these little
dots to keep flowing.
So that's one reason that the choke point
has become more vital than ever.
The other reason is China.
(subdued music)
China rose to become a
manufacturing superpower.
They make a lot of stuff and
they send it to the West.
And a lot of that comes
through this choke point.
And all of this vital trade is happening
in a region that is full
of unstable governments,
rising anti-Western
militias and Somali pirates
making this route precarious and dangerous
and subject to problems.
So Djibouti has become this vital place
here at the choke point,
an incredibly important strategic location
in a sea of turmoil.
Okay, but there's more.
In addition to all of this
global economy importance,
there's also regional
importance to Djibouti.
Notice Djibouti's neighbor, Ethiopia,
the second most populous
country in Africa,
and as you can see, one
that is totally landlocked.
It is not good to be a big
country that is landlocked
because the water is where we trade.
So Djibouti is the gateway
to Ethiopia's millions of
people to trade with the world.
95% of Ethiopia's trade
passes through Djibouti.
So Djibouti, this colonial
creation from France in the 1880s
is now once again an incredibly
important place on the map.
It's become, once again, a
highly strategic location.
(inquisitive music)
And when there are highly
strategic locations,
superpowers start moving in.
In 2011, Djibouti approved Japan,
a pacifist sort of non-military country,
to open a military base on Djibouti,
their one and only foreign military base.
Then you have Italy who set up
a military base here in 2013.
Spain and Germany also have
a military presence here.
They're not permanently
hosted with a base,
they're actually hosted by France,
and the soldiers live in
these hotels permanently.
Okay. That's not weird at all.
But yeah, as you can see,
the great powers are back.
They're back in Djibouti
like the old days,
not to compete with one another,
but to all band together
to police this vital choke
point so that the global economy
that has brought prosperity
to all of us can stay stable.
Everything keeps flowing.
Everyone is happy.
And this solved a big
problem for Djibouti,
who, again, didn't have a big industry
or any kind of resource.
They make a lot of money
off of these leases
to foreign countries, which
has helped build their economy.
And like the old days,
when one side shows up,
the rival won't be far behind.
(tense music)
- China has agreed to set up
a support base in Djibouti.
- So the Chinese base is right here,
and they're gonna be watching
us as we are watching them.
- In 2016, Djibouti announces
that they've been talking to China
and that they've agreed to give them land
to open their own military base,
which was built and
opened right down the road
from the American base in 2017.
So China says they're
there because of pirates.
Pirates have been wreaking
havoc in this area.
So they're there to stabilize
their economic interests
because of pirates.
But as we discovered in
our deep dive on pirates,
by 2017, the pirate
issue was basically over.
There was almost no
hijackings in this region.
I mean, look at this graph.
Oh, and the Chinese base
has this big deep pier
that is like large enough to
handle an aircraft carrier
and nuclear submarines.
So this isn't about pirates.
China also did the most China
thing when they moved in here,
which was instead of just
building a base, they also came
with all of these big-ticket
infrastructure projects
as like gifts to win
the favor of the locals.
We're talking railway, pipeline,
port, all very expensive,
all putting Djibouti into
a lot of debt to China.
They're doing this all over Africa,
which we talk about in
another deep dive video
we did on the topic mapping all
of China's giant infrastructure
projects in Africa
and what that means.
Man, a lot of shout outs
to other videos today, huh?
So Djibouti is now the only place on earth
where the United States and
China, these two rivals,
have military bases
right next to each other.
And so far everyone's been playing nice.
There's been no shenanigans
other than both sides accusing each other
of spying on each other constantly.
Oh, and there was the lasers.
The U.S. says that China
was pointing lasers
into the eyes of pilots
while they were taking off,
which like if they really did
that, that's just like, why?
Why would you do that?
Like, why did you do that? Don't do that.
Okay, but Djibouti doesn't
let every country in.
Russia wanted to have
their own base in Djibouti.
And Djibouti said no.
It probably helped
that the American national
security advisor flew to Djibouti
and told them that the U.S.
would double how much they're
paying for their lease
if Djibouti didn't let Russia in.
(gentle music)
Okay, but what about the people?
Djibouti isn't just one big military base.
There's almost a million
people who live here
and their day-to-day probably consists
of a lot of jet engine sounds.
I got to talk to my old grad
school professor, David Vine,
who is an expert on U.S. military bases
and how they affect the locals.
- So what we were talking
about is a foreign government,
foreign military occupying large
swaths of land, fenced off,
and hosting large amounts of weaponry,
high-powered weaponry of many, many kinds.
(Hassan speaking foreign language)
- Because these bases are so
close to like the big city,
there have been accidents,
especially with drones.
The U.S. used to take off their
drones and some would fall
and actually crash onto like
civilian infrastructure.
So they had to open a separate airstrip
(Hassan speaking foreign language)
- Apart from occasionally
running over cows,
the soldiers mostly keep to themselves.
U.S. soldiers don't even go
into the city to like buy stuff.
All of it is flown in
creating a little slice of
America right in Djibouti.
Like, they don't even drink
the water from Djibouti.
It's all flown in.
(Hassan speaking foreign language)
- And then there's the dictator.
- Well, I wanna welcome President Guelleh
and his delegation here today.
- The U.S. base in particular,
but also the French and Chinese bases,
which are the largest of the collection,
are all helping to prop
up undemocratic regime
that has, you know, been accused
of widespread human rights abuses
- Every time a foreign power
makes a deal with Djibouti
and pays them a lot of money
in exchange for them
being able to be there,
they basically validate
this terrible dictator
who's been in power for 25 years.
There's no real elections,
free press, freedom of speech,
plenty of human rights abuses.
But on the other side,
there's at least one way
that regular people in Djibouti
benefit from all of this.
Fewer people go hungry today
than at the conclusion of the civil war.
And even though the economy is still poor,
all of this foreign aid
still does support it.
Is that worth it to them?
I don't actually know.
And another version of this
video that I wanna do someday
is to go there and talk to the people
and hear what their thoughts
are about the bases in Djibouti
and what that feels like
to live so close to all of
these foreign militaries.
For now, we're talking
about the geography, the
history, the geopolitics.
(upbeat music)
Okay, speaking of geopolitics,
there is another angle to this story
that is devilishly
complicated to get into.
And I'm not gonna get into
all the juicy details.
You'll understand why when
I start talking about it.
It has to do with the regional
geopolitics, the rivalries,
and the concerns and the issues
of all of these countries that
are right next to Djibouti,
not just the outside powers.
I want to just give you a little sampling
of what this looks like
because it's pretty wild.
So you have all these Gulf countries,
and some of them are not
totally on the same team,
but almost all of them are
thinking about the future
and they're realizing that oil
is not gonna be a big part of their future
because oil is not gonna be
a big part of any of our future hopefully.
And they're realizing
that they're going to need
to invest in the Horn of
Africa, this region here,
which they believe is
probably gonna be the future
of their food, their future bread basket.
So hold that for a second
and then look at Ethiopia and Eritrea.
Ethiopia, as we mentioned,
uses Djibouti as their
gateway to the world.
They need it to feed
their millions of people.
All of this geopolitics is
also playing out in Djibouti,
this little country
that has to navigate everyone's interests.
So here's a quick episode of this drama
to give you an idea of what it looks like.
(intense music)
The United Arab Emirates, UAE,
used to be like best
friends with Djibouti.
It was like one of their
most important partners.
The UAE built and owned this giant port
that basically runs
Djibouti's entire economy.
But then the UAE got really
close to Djibouti's neighbor
and kind of enemy Eritrea.
This was very worrisome
because Djibouti doesn't want Eritrea
to become the new Djibouti.
They're a mortal threat.
They don't want the UAE to
just shut down Djibouti's,
like, strategic offering.
Okay, fast forward to like 2017,
the UAE with their close
friend, Saudi Arabia,
are in a feud with Qatar,
which also has a military
presence in Djibouti
right up here on this border.
Now that Qatar and the UAE
are fighting with each other,
they turn to Djibouti
and say, "Hey, you are
too close with the UAE.
We're out of here."
Qatar takes their soldiers
out of this border area,
and right away,
Eritrea takes some of
this land from Djibouti.
This may seem like some
petty border skirmishes,
but remember where we are here.
This is the vital choke
point, Bab-el-Mandeb,
every inch of land matters.
Every little conflict
could be the spark that
stops the global economy.
And what this little flare up shows us
is how Djibouti finds itself
in the center of conflicts
between other countries
that it kind of doesn't
want to be in the middle of,
but, like, has found
itself in the middle of
because it hosts all of their militaries.
But wait, there's more.
Djibouti is actually really good at this.
They know how to play the game
and to play all these
powers off of each other
and we'll see what happens next.
So they're kind of beholden to the UAE,
UAE has way too much leverage over them.
So finally it all comes to a head
and they kick the UAE out
from this really vital port,
and they give a massive chunk
of it to, wait for it, China,
the new arrival to Djibouti
that no one wants to mess with.
They now have the port
and Djibouti is now on their side
and the UAE can't do anything about it.
Djibouti saved itself from one power
by pleasing a bigger power.
Do you see how this works?
Do you see what game they're playing here?
(subdued music)
So that is why this tiny
country in East Africa
is so important.
It's kind of the
definition of geopolitics,
politics happening because of geography.
To project legitimacy.
This choke point is only going
to become more important.
Day by day, we're seeing it happen.
I mean, like right now
as I'm filming this,
the Houthis rebels
are like potentially
cutting internet cables
in this choke point.
- Three crew members have
been killed in a Houthis-
- The first death since Houthis rebels
began attacking shipping in the Red Sea.
- After months of bombing merchant ships
to punish the West for
supporting the IDF war in Gaza.
I mean, it's this kind of threat
that Djibouti was set up to handle.
That is why all these
foreign militaries are here.
And yet for me, there is a subtler threat
that is emerging here,
which you can see when you
just look at this map of bases.
Djibouti hosts rival countries
during a time when we
are transitioning away
from a rules-based order
where all the great powers
have an incentive to work
together under one system
that is dominated by the United States
that deeply benefits the
United States and its allies.
But that works because the United States
imposes and protects those rules.
Those rules are being challenged.
And what is emerging is
a system that is messier,
more disruptive to these reliable rules
that have kept everything stable,
kept the United States on top.
And unfortunately we know all too well
what happens when great powers
start competing with
each other more and more
over vital resources
and vital geographies.
In fact, most of the history of war
is what happens when great powers
are competing with each other.
It's ugly, it's messy, it's violent.
It provokes a zero-sum way of thinking,
competition racing to secure and control
and exploit vital geographies
like strategic choke points
that lead into the most
important waterway on the planet.
As this rivalry heats up,
Djibouti's role is going
to become more complex.
Its government will continue
to do what it's done,
playing the big powers off each other,
exploiting its great real
estate to benefit itself.
But I believe that there comes a point
in every escalating conflict
where you kind of have to choose sides.
I want Djibouti to continue
to embody the positive sum thinking
that has kept the world relatively stable
these last 70 years.
But it's definitely playing
with a very delicate balancing act
and there's a chance
that it could stumble.
So as you all know, I
will be keeping an eye
on the global order as well as Djibouti
to try to see where this is going,
to see if the great powers
can continue to cooperate
and compete, but cooperate.
Or if we're heading back into the old days
where competition threatens
to rip the world apart.
I don't think it's inevitable,
but it's gonna take effort to avoid it.
(subdued music)
I've been sleeping every
night in the desert.
Up here in the northwest
corner of Saudi Arabia.
(weighty music)
It's quiet up here.
All you can hear is the wind
and the sand that it whips
off these endless dunes.
(sand rustles)
But not far from where I
sleep there's a new sound.
(construction rumbles and drones)
For years I've been hearing
about this trillion-dollar futuristic city
that the kingdom of Saudi Arabia
is building atop this sand.
They're calling it Neom,
and they're investing a huge amount
of their vast oil wealth
into making it come to life.
I've been hearing about all
the reasons it can't work,
how this is all just a
mirage of royal ambitions.
And yet even from space,
you can see that they're building it,
they're building something.
Why would anyone try to
build a futuristic city
in a barren desert?
That is a question I've
had for a very long time,
and one I intend to get to the bottom of.
(inquisitive music)
So I'm going into Neom to
see what it looks like,
to get a sense of its scale.
We're looking at this
fleet of dump trucks.
The amount of construction
activity is insane,
and it hasn't stopped as we've
been driving along The Line.
The magnitude, I've never
seen anything close.
They're building mountains out there.
I'm joined by my friend Solom,
who was born in a tent out here.
He knows this desert better than anyone,
every dune, every valley.
All the secret water spots
hidden deep in red rock slot canyons.
I asked Solom to bring
me out into the desert,
not only to get up close on
the construction of Neom,
but also to show me how
people live out here,
to introduce me to members of his tribe,
how they've survived for centuries.
Nomadic Bedouin, who
represent the origin story
of this desert kingdom.
(Bedouin people laughing)
I wanted to put a human face
to this collision of worlds, old and new.
(wondrous music)
I believe this little shape on the map
represents the story of Saudi Arabia,
where it came from, how it got here,
and why it is attempting to
build these cities in the sand.
(truck horn blaring)
I'm officially in Neom,
and let me tell you
what I'm seeing so far.
(trucks droning)
Trucks, trucks, trucks.
Dump trucks, cargo trucks,
trucks carrying excavators,
trucks carrying more trucks.
I've never seen so many
trucks in my entire life.
Oh, and these roads, a
lot of them are brand new,
a lot of them don't even
show up on Google Maps.
Like I'm looking at my phone
and I'm just sort of
floating in no man's land
because these are all brand-new roads.
This is new, everything
is popping up so quickly.
(laughs) There's so many trucks.
(upbeat music)
All of the sudden,
Solom turned off one of
these pristinely new roads.
Why do you deflate the tires?
- For the dune.
- We're now gonna start driving
just into the desert.
(bright music)
Wow, this car can go everywhere.
Are we going up this dune?
- Yeah.
- Oh, wow.
(engine revs)
- Oh, yeah.
- Whoo. Geez, this is insane.
(ethereal music)
(Johnny laughs)
(bright music)
Man.
It's gorgeous.
Okay, now we're really in the desert.
We found a little canyon to camp in.
(fire crackling)
And while I thought we'd
be eating granola bars
or canned soup, Solom had other plans.
- [Solom] Have you
tried camel meat before?
- [Johnny] Nuh-uh.
- You will try it tonight.
- Really?
- Hashi. Hashi is the young camel.
- [Johnny] Ah, rice with camel meat.
The evening tradition here is to wind down
with a cup of coffee.
Saudi coffee is unroasted and
green, infused with cardamom.
It's a different taste, I like it though.
But it's still very caffeinated.
Oh, and then after the coffee comes...
- Tea?
- Ah, thank you.
Which, again, is very delicious,
but how can they drink so
much coffee before bed?
Yeah, I can't drink too much
because I-
- Oh yeah.
- The caffeine, I won't be able to sleep.
- Yeah.
- [Johnny] In the morning
I'll drink a lot of it.
- Okay.
(gentle music)
- Wow.
Mm, wow. That's good.
So until what age did
you live in the desert?
- Maybe until seven.
- Till seven?
- Yeah.
- Did you like it?
- Yeah, I like it.
- Yeah.
- I like it.
It's so rare to find families.
Real families living in the desert.
(Johnny laughing)
The people that we are going
to, they are real Bedouins.
(Bedouins people laughing)
But when we moved to the city
I study.
(cars honking)
I go back.
- Oh, you go back to the desert?
- Yeah.
(gentle music)
Even for me, I like to
have a job in the city,
but I want the Bedouin life.
I want them to stay.
- Soon we'll meet the Bedouin nomads
who sleep under these stars every night.
Look at this night full
of incredible stars.
Wow.
The Saudi desert is proving
to be exceptionally peaceful,
despite the army of
trucks that, by the way,
are still working here
in the dead of night.
They don't ever stop
and haven't for years.
(Johnny exhales)
It is so silent here.
My brain doesn't know what to do about it.
It's so silent and...
(serene music)
(Johnny chuckles)
But as the sun rises
and Solom feeds me dates and green coffee,
oh, and of course more tea,
I'm thinking about my mission for today.
(driving music)
My plan is to drive all throughout Neom,
to all the big construction sites
and show you what they're
planning on building out here
with their initial budget of $500 billion,
which has since ballooned to
an estimated $1.5 trillion.
And you're about to see why.
So I made it to the coast,
and I'm looking at the beautiful Red Sea,
which is a very beautiful
kind of blue in fact.
- [Presenter] This is Oxagon,
the place where ideas
can change the world.
- [Johnny] Oxagon is planned
to be their futuristic industrial city.
Half of it built on the water.
It'll be a port where
shipping can connect the world
to a bunch of high-tech manufacturing,
research, and logistics.
And there's Sindalah,
which is gonna be right
here on the Red Sea.
It's going to be a luxury resort island
with plenty of parking for yachts.
Hello.
We picked up a hitchhiker
who has been working
on Sindalah for years.
How's it looking in Sindalah?
- [Hitch Hiker] Finished like 99%.
- Really?
- Yeah.
(upbeat music)
Sindalah.
(drone buzzes)
And then there's Magna,
(light fluttery music)
which is actually the name of
one of these coastal villages
we've just been driving next
to that is no longer a village.
They forcibly relocated
thousands of people
for this project.
Atop the ruins of these
villages, the kingdom
is building 12 luxury coastal
resorts and communities.
(birds squawking)
Hey, just one quick clarification here,
all of those visuals are 3D renders.
They are visualizations done by Neom
to see what they want this to look like.
This stuff doesn't exist yet,
and I think that maybe is obvious,
but it looks so real
that I just want to
just make crystal clear.
I'm showing a lot of this stuff
from the hypey promo visuals
that have come out from Neom.
So that's one thing.
Also, check out some of this footage I got
while I was on a dune.
It's floating around on this dune.
This is me shooting from the drone,
but suddenly on the other
side of this massive dune,
there are these green circles.
When I was planning my
trip to Saudi Arabia,
I got really interested in these things,
but that has nothing to do with Neom,
so I hopped on the phone with
my new colleague, Christophe,
and asked him to go down
the deep dive rabbit hole
of why there's a bunch of green
circles in the Saudi desert.
And he did so,
and he made an entire video
about what he learned.
That video is live right now
on our new channel tunnel_vision,
I think you're gonna like it.
(bright music)
Built on some pretty wild
designs, ideas and concepts,
including...
- [Presenter] A vast
subterranean digital community
inside a mountain,
Magna, the coast of Neom.
- [Johnny] Yeah, right there is perfect.
(Solom speaking foreign language)
- And then there's Trojena
up here in the mountains.
Yes, there are big mountains here.
It's going to be a luxury
tourist destination
for adventure and wellness retreats,
complete with an artificial
lake and outdoor activities
like mountain biking and skiing.
Yes, I just said skiing.
Up here in the mountains it
gets kind of cold in the winter
and snow falls.
Definitely not enough for skiing,
but enough for them to make
fake snow and make ski slopes.
They're building a manmade lake,
in fact, they're doing it right now,
I'm looking up at the mountain
and seeing the plumes of
smoke from the dynamite
that they're using
(explosions boom)
to do whatever they need to do
to build an artificial lake.
Oh, and by the way,
that's the mountain
where Moses talked to God
and got the 10 Commandments
like a few thousand years ago.
- There is no freedom without the law.
(lofty music)
Who is on the Lord's side?
- [Presenter] Welcome to
Trojena, the mountains of Neom.
(Johnny laughing)
- This is all so strange.
And then of course, the one
you've maybe heard about.
(grand airy music)
And yes, it's being built.
I've been driving along it all morning
and I can't really fathom what I'm seeing.
I continue to have my mind
blown at a scale of this.
They say The Line is
gonna be a futuristic city
that stretches 170 kilometers
and run on renewable energy
and artificial intelligence.
They want 10 million
people to come live here,
like a whole New York city of people
inside of this line in the desert.
Just the digging alone,
the amount of earth that
they're moving is jaw dropping.
The magnitude is like they're
building mountains out there
and moving so much earth.
(crashing music)
Now I thought I had seen
a lot of trucks before,
but as I drove along The Line,
I started to get slightly dizzy.
Having a hard time processing
the scale of all of this,
all of these machines working nonstop,
every hour of every day for years.
Moving sand, making mountains
and carving a straight
line into the desert.
(wind rustling)
All of this seems impossible.
So much of the reporting on Neom
has been focused on how
implausible, expensive,
and delusional this project is.
And that's all well and good
if that's what you wanna focus on,
but to me that's not that interesting.
What I'm most interested
in understanding is why.
(gentle music)
We found a little cave
last night and camped here.
Solom invited some of his friends out.
Hey guys.
- Hi.
- How's it going?
- Good.
- This is so cool, right?
- Yeah, it is.
(fire crackling)
- [Johnny] We all sat around the fire,
me listening while they
laughed and joked in Arabic.
(Solom and friends speaking Arabic)
And then began cooking yet
another delicious meal.
This time, goat cooked in
goat milk with flatbread.
Wow, this is awesome.
- Yeah.
(Solom speaking Arabic)
- Mm, wow. So good.
I'm admittedly a little groggy
after sleeping a few
nights on the desert floor.
(warm music)
We're just sledding down
a massive dune in a car
and it's as smooth as butter.
Where they're making Trojena
it's gonna be kind of crazy.
To have skiing in Saudi Arabia, right?
- That's a big change here.
- Yeah.
- It was like a hiking trail.
Really?
- [Solom] But with this, no, this is new.
- Today, Solom is introducing me
to members of his tribe.
Is this them?
Hello.
It'll be the polar opposite
of yesterday's tour through
Neom's construction.
He put on his traditional Saudi clothing
so as not to surprise
the members of his tribe
that he has indeed
become a modern city man.
(gentle music)
We arrived to a remote patch of desert
where a few tents are set up.
The elder of this family
warmly invites me in.
Johnny, hi.
To sit for coffee.
(Bedouin peoples speaking Arabic)
And then of course more tea.
Wow.
And at this point, I'm just
embracing the caffeine.
They tell me that the only Westerners
they've ever seen out here
are the ones looking for oil.
And that it's very strange
to see me showing up
to learn about their culture
and especially with a camera.
(Bedouin peoples speaking Arabic)
- [Johnny] So how long
have you lived here?
- [Tribesman] This is two months here.
- Months?
- Yeah.
- Wow.
(Tribesman speaking Arabic)
(sheep bleating)
- I got to meet their animals,
extended members of this nomadic family.
(camel grunting)
So this family's been here on this site,
and they'll move again when
the season tells them to.
They basically are here
grazing their camels
and their goats.
And God, they've got a beautiful view.
Oh, my God, those mountains.
So wait, he's the shepherd?
You're the shepherd?
- Yeah.
- Wow. That's cool.
Do you ever get lost in the desert?
(Solom speaking Arabic)
- No.
- No, he's a pro.
He's a pro on that donkey.
(Bedouin people speaking Arabic)
- These people's lives depend
on moving these animals
through the desert in
search for scarce food.
A theme I hear from a lot
of people who live out here
is the, just sense of peace
and simplicity that they get,
that they realize that the
city could never bring.
What do you like about out
here that makes you stay?
(tribesman speaking Arabic)
So when you go to the city-
- Ah, city.
- City, no.
(both laugh)
This is a better life.
Man, this sunset is gorgeous.
(tribesman singing)
Okay. Yeah, yeah, that's good.
(warm adventurous music)
As the group faces east
to perform their fourth of
five prayers they do each day,
I'm looking west.
(gentle music)
Just over those mountains,
the kingdom of Saudi Arabia
is digging a giant line in the sand.
Working day and night
to reshape this desert,
building their high-tech eco city.
For most of its history,
this was the way of life
out here on this peninsula.
And it may have remained such to this day,
but eventually the Bedouin
on this peninsula united,
and unbeknownst to anyone,
was sitting atop a sea of black gold.
- [Narrator] Oil in commercial quantities,
averaging about 200,000 barrels a day.
To handle this huge volume,
the expanding program requires an increase
of permanent personnel
to a total of more than 15,000 Arabs.
- [Johnny] Oil changed everything.
The kingdom rapidly modernized.
- [Narrator] The king
sees the oil development
as the greatest single means
to modernize his country
and improve the living
standards of his people.
- [Johnny] All while still
maintaining a deep connection
with Islamic law,
(muezzin sings)
and the rules and norms of Bedouin life.
And despite this rapid modernization,
hundreds of thousands of people
still maintain the nomadic lifestyle.
It is a link to their past.
(tribesman chatter in Arabic)
Nice.
- [Solom] They're talking about something
that they see it these days.
The people travel by like bike-
- Cycling? Oh.
- Yeah.
- The conversation goes into the night
and I knew I had to ask them about Neom.
Can you ask them what their thoughts are
on all the building that's happening?
I have to be sensitive here
'cause I'm reminded where I am.
Saudi Arabia isn't a place
where citizens, nomads or not,
can speak critically about their kingdom.
I got nervous looks and vague answers.
But one thing is for certain
that the Saudi government
has been paying and compensating anyone
who has been affected by these projects.
(tribesmen speaking Arabic)
- [Johnny] Out of respect,
I decide not to push it,
it's not worth it.
(tribesmen speaking Arabic)
- [Johnny] We're sitting
around a huge platter
of camel meat and fragrant rice.
So where I'm from, there's no camels.
- Ah.
- No camels,
I've never seen a camel until yesterday.
The elder generously
showing his hospitality
by finding the juiciest
chunks of camel meat and fat
and passing them to me.
Thank you.
(elder speaking Arabic)
- Yeah.
And I'm realizing that
this moment is a glimpse
into one of the oldest-surviving
cultures on earth.
(elder speaking Arabic)
- Thank you.
(Bedouin people speaking Arabic)
(gentle music)
- The family invites us
to sleep near their tent.
Another night, another sky full of stars.
I'm really feeling it,
just how fast the change
has come to this desert,
where nomads whose movement
and lifestyle hark back to
the earliest civilizations
and who are now living
a stone's throw away
from the construction of a futuristic city
that is attempting to
define the next chapter
of human civilization.
(distressing music)
It feels like too much to process.
(gentle music)
(elder speaking Arabic)
- I couldn't help but feel worried
for this link to the past.
(Bedouin people speaking Arabic)
(Johnny and Bedouin people laughing)
(wind whispering)
- So oil transformed this desert,
but soon a problem began to arise.
(serious music)
Slowly, the world has started
coming to terms with the reality
that burning oil to run our world
is turning the planet
into a place that's not
conducive for human life.
(futuristic music)
The International Energy Agency predicts
that the world will hit
peak oil demand in 2030,
at which time demand will start to fall.
Other predictions say it'll take longer,
but everyone agrees
that the future of this world is not oil.
This is bad news for Saudi Arabia,
a country that has nothing but oil.
- [Announcer] Aramco, the
state-owned oil company,
second-quarter profit are
tumbling by more than a third
from last year's record highs.
- Oil transformed this desert kingdom
into a modern, powerful country.
And in order for them
to retain that status,
they're going to need to
use the money from that oil
to transform themselves again.
Enter, Neom.
(futuristic music)
Saudi Arabia wants to
replace its oil economy
with new economies, new industries,
some of which they want to invent.
This kingdom that has been
historically closed is now open,
welcoming tourists for the first time.
- [Presenter] Welcome to
Arabia. Get your visa now.
- Let's go to Sindalah!
Are here.
- [Johnny] Hoping to attract the world,
this is something neighboring
Dubai has done successfully.
- [Presenter] The spirit of Dubai.
- But Saudi Arabia plans to
do it on a whole new level.
I'll tell you one thing,
the water here is beautiful.
On that note, I was surprised
at how welcome I felt here.
Every person I met
greeted me with kindness
and eagerness to show me their culture.
(tribesman chatter in Arabic)
But it's not just about tourism,
Neom is manufacturing,
sustainability technology,
sports, education, media,
and even an attempt to
reinvent cities themselves.
(inquisitive music)
They also want to use all this oil money
to stay on top of global energy.
All of this hot sun is
great for solar energy.
And while driving around,
I saw endless fields of wind turbines.
And they can use this to make
new forms of hydrogen energy
that they can ship around the world.
And the reason why all these promo videos
look like a Hollywood movie
is because they can't do this
without investors from the outside world.
(presenter speaking Arabic)
- [Johnny] They need
people to come live here.
- [Vlogger] So my
husband got offered a job
for Neom in Saudi Arabia,
and we decided to make the move.
- [Johnny] They need them to play here,
raise children here,
somehow have a life here,
and most crucially to
invest in these projects.
- And what are we calling it?
- The Line.
- [Johnny] So not unlike a startup,
Neom is pitching the world
on this impossible-sounding vision
with the hopes that people
will buy it, invest in it,
and make some version of it a reality.
So do you feel excited about it Neom?
Like-
- Yes.
- Yeah? Why?
- I wouldn't do this
business without Neom.
- Oh wow.
- Before Neom.
- Wow.
- Everyone wanna, like,
check out on internet what is Neom.
Then they need a tour guide.
To have more than 30 tour
guides working with me.
- Wow.
- So it's a big business now
and it's all because of Neom.
- [Johnny] So while Solom
is seeing the benefits of this project,
the effects for others in
this region are less certain.
We're driving by some of the towns
that have been demolished.
The people forced to move
to make way for the construction of Neom.
They were given money to rebuild
their lives somewhere else.
But some refused to leave,
signing a petition to
protest this forced eviction.
One even posted to social
media voicing his outrage,
a risky move in a place
where freedom of speech
isn't really a thing.
(gunshots pop)
Soon he was locked in a shootout
with security forces that left him dead.
- [Reporter] This is when Saudi officials
reportedly handed over the body
of Abdul Rahim al-Huwaiti to his tribe.
His family denies the official narrative
that Rahim was a terrorist.
- [Johnny] At least 47 other villagers
were detained on terror-related charges,
and five of them are now on death row.
(gentle optimistic music)
The scale and riskiness of these projects
speaks to the scale of
Saudi Arabia's challenge.
They need something to keep
them afloat after oil goes away,
so they're betting the family farm
on a few massive projects.
Many will likely fail,
but even if a few of
these work out as planned,
it could be their next oil.
Lifting this kingdom into the future,
that's the calculus here.
But what's clear is that this kingdom
isn't stopping anytime soon.
(grand airy music)
- Our economy is in recession
and the civilized world
faces unprecedented dangers.
Yet the state of our union
has never been stronger.
(crowd cheering)
(subdued music)
(subdued music continues)